<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?><?xml-stylesheet type="text/css" href="http://www.textcreationpartnership.org/docs/code/pfs.css"?><TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
   <teiHeader>
      <fileDesc>
         <titleStmt>
            <title>Annus tenebrosus, or The dark year Or astrologicall iudgements upon two lunar eclipses, and one admirable eclips of the sun, all visible in England, 1652. Together with a short method how to judge the effects of eclipses. / By William Lilly, student in astrologie.</title>
            <author>Lilly, William, 1602-1681.</author>
         </titleStmt>
         <extent>Approx. 173KB of XML-encoded text transcribed from 41 1-bit group-IV TIFF page images.</extent>
         <publicationStmt>
            <publisher>Text Creation Partnership,</publisher>
            <pubPlace>Ann Arbor, MI ; Oxford (UK) :</pubPlace>
            <date when="2016-02">2016-02 (EEBO-TCP Phase 2).</date>
            <idno type="DLPS">A88277</idno><idno type="EEBO-CITATION">99862908</idno>
  <idno type="VID">115088</idno>
  <idno type="EEBO-PROQUEST">2248541908</idno>
  
            <idno type="STC">Wing L2209</idno>
            <idno type="STC">Thomason E656_23</idno>
            <idno type="STC">ESTC R202712</idno>
            <idno type="PROQUEST">99862908</idno>
            <availability><p>This keyboarded and encoded edition of the work described above is co-owned by the
    institutions providing financial support to the Early English Books Online Text Creation
    Partnership. This text is available for reuse, according to the terms of <ref target="https://creativecommons.org/publicdomain/zero/1.0/"> Creative Commons 0 1.0 Universal
    licence</ref>. The text can be copied, modified, distributed and performed, even for commercial
    purposes, all without asking permission.</p></availability>
         </publicationStmt>
         <seriesStmt>
            <title>Early English books online text creation partnership.</title>
         </seriesStmt>
         <notesStmt><relatedItem type="facs" target="https://data.historicaltexts.jisc.ac.uk/view?pubId=eebo-99862908e"/>
            <note>(EEBO-TCP ; phase 2, no. A88277)</note>
            <note>Transcribed from: (Early English Books Online ; image set 115088)</note>
            <note>Images scanned from microfilm: (Thomason Tracts ; 101:E656[23])</note>
         </notesStmt>
         <sourceDesc>
            <biblFull>
               <titleStmt>
                  <title>Annus tenebrosus, or The dark year Or astrologicall iudgements upon two lunar eclipses, and one admirable eclips of the sun, all visible in England, 1652. Together with a short method how to judge the effects of eclipses. / By William Lilly, student in astrologie.</title>
                  <author>Lilly, William, 1602-1681.</author>
               </titleStmt>
               <extent>[16], 63, [1] p. : ill. (woodcuts)  </extent>
               <publicationStmt>
                  <publisher>Printed for the Company of Stationers, and H. Blunden at the Castle in Corn-hill,</publisher>
                  <pubPlace>London :</pubPlace>
                  <date>1652.</date>
               </publicationStmt>
               <notesStmt>
                  <note>Annotation on Thomason copy: "Catamite, and" inserted with a caret between 'Lilly,' and 'student'; "march 22 1651"; and the last number of the date has been marked through.</note>
                  <note>Reproduction of the original in the British Library.</note>
               </notesStmt>
            </biblFull>
         </sourceDesc>
      </fileDesc>
      <encodingDesc>
         <projectDesc>
            <p>Created by converting TCP files to TEI P5 using tcp2tei.xsl,
      TEI @ Oxford.
      </p>
         </projectDesc>
         <editorialDecl>
            <p>EEBO-TCP is a partnership between the Universities of Michigan and Oxford and the publisher ProQuest to create accurately transcribed and encoded texts based on the image sets published by ProQuest via their Early English Books Online (EEBO) database (http://eebo.chadwyck.com). The general aim of EEBO-TCP is to encode one copy (usually the first edition) of every monographic English-language title published between 1473 and 1700 available in EEBO.</p>
            <p>EEBO-TCP aimed to produce large quantities of textual data within the usual project restraints of time and funding, and therefore chose to create diplomatic transcriptions (as opposed to critical editions) with light-touch, mainly structural encoding based on the Text Encoding Initiative (http://www.tei-c.org).</p>
            <p>The EEBO-TCP project was divided into two phases. The 25,363 texts created during Phase 1 of the project have been released into the public domain as of 1 January 2015. Anyone can now take and use these texts for their own purposes, but we respectfully request that due credit and attribution is given to their original source.</p>
            <p>Users should be aware of the process of creating the TCP texts, and therefore of any assumptions that can be made about the data.</p>
            <p>Text selection was based on the New Cambridge Bibliography of English Literature (NCBEL). If an author (or for an anonymous work, the title) appears in NCBEL, then their works are eligible for inclusion. Selection was intended to range over a wide variety of subject areas, to reflect the true nature of the print record of the period. In general, first editions of a works in English were prioritized, although there are a number of works in other languages, notably Latin and Welsh, included and sometimes a second or later edition of a work was chosen if there was a compelling reason to do so.</p>
            <p>Image sets were sent to external keying companies for transcription and basic encoding. Quality assurance was then carried out by editorial teams in Oxford and Michigan. 5% (or 5 pages, whichever is the greater) of each text was proofread for accuracy and those which did not meet QA standards were returned to the keyers to be redone. After proofreading, the encoding was enhanced and/or corrected and characters marked as illegible were corrected where possible up to a limit of 100 instances per text. Any remaining illegibles were encoded as &lt;gap&gt;s. Understanding these processes should make clear that, while the overall quality of TCP data is very good, some errors will remain and some readable characters will be marked as illegible. Users should bear in mind that in all likelihood such instances will never have been looked at by a TCP editor.</p>
            <p>The texts were encoded and linked to page images in accordance with level 4 of the TEI in Libraries guidelines.</p>
            <p>Copies of the texts have been issued variously as SGML (TCP schema; ASCII text with mnemonic sdata character entities); displayable XML (TCP schema; characters represented either as UTF-8 Unicode or text strings within braces); or lossless XML (TEI P5, characters represented either as UTF-8 Unicode or TEI g elements).</p>
            <p>Full documentation of the original data capture process is available from the <ref target="http://www.textcreationpartnership.org/docs/.">Text Creation Partnership web site</ref>.
   All versions of the texts are now archived and freely available for download. See <ref target="https://textcreationpartnership.org/faq/#faq05">the TCP Download FAQ</ref>
   for detailed information. The TEI P5 versions are also freely available from the <ref target="https://github.com/textcreationpartnership">TCP Github repository</ref>.</p>
         </editorialDecl>
         <listPrefixDef>
            <prefixDef ident="tcp" matchPattern="([0-9\-]+):([0-9IVX]+)" replacementPattern="http://eebo.chadwyck.com/downloadtiff?vid=$1&amp;page=$2"/>
            <prefixDef ident="char" matchPattern="(.+)" replacementPattern="https://raw.githubusercontent.com/textcreationpartnership/Texts/master/tcpchars.xml#$1"/>
         </listPrefixDef>
      </encodingDesc>
      <profileDesc>
         <langUsage>
            <language ident="eng">eng</language>
         </langUsage>
         <textClass>
            <keywords scheme="http://authorities.loc.gov/">
               <term type="topical_term">Lunar eclipses --  1652 --  Early works to 1800.</term>
               <term type="topical_term">Solar eclipses --  1652 --  Early works to 1800.</term>
               <term type="topical_term">Astrology --  Early works to 1800.</term>
            </keywords>
         </textClass>
      </profileDesc>
      <revisionDesc>
         <change>
            <date>2014-05 </date>
            <label>SPi Global</label>Keyed and coded from ProQuest page images </change>
         <change>
            <date>2015-02 </date>
            <label>Kate Allen </label>Sampled and proofread </change>
         <change>
            <date>2015-02 </date>
            <label>Kate Allen</label>Text and markup reviewed and edited </change>
         <change>
            <date>2015-03 </date>
            <label>pfs</label>Batch review (QC) and XML conversion </change>
      <change><date>2021-05 </date><label>lb</label>TEI P5 conversion </change></revisionDesc>
   </teiHeader>
   <text>
      <front>
         <div type="title_page">
            <pb facs="tcp:115088:1"/>
            <p>
               <hi>ANNUS TENEBROSUS,</hi> OR THE DARK YEAR. Or Astrologicall Iudgements upon two <hi>Lunar Eclipses,</hi> and one admirable <hi>Eclips</hi> of the <hi>Sun,</hi> all visible in <hi>England,</hi> 1652.</p>
            <p>Together with a short Method how to judge the effects of ECLIPSES.</p>
            <p>A True Type of the <hi>Suns</hi> great <hi>Eclipse.</hi>
            </p>
            <figure>
               <figDesc>stylized depiction of an eclipse</figDesc>
            </figure>
            <q>
               <l>Quod priscis vetitum erat, quod{que} Parabolis</l>
               <l>Vix olim licuit dicere; Nunc mihi</l>
               <l>Nudis datur venia promere verbis:</l>
               <l>Ut fiant dociles viri.</l>
            </q>
            <p>
               <hi>By</hi> WILLIAM LILLY, <hi>Student in Astrologie.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>
               <hi>London,</hi> Printed for the Company of <hi>Stationers,</hi> and <hi>H. Blunden</hi> at the Castle in Corn-hill, 1652.</p>
         </div>
         <div type="to_the_reader">
            <pb facs="tcp:115088:2"/>
            <pb facs="tcp:115088:2"/>
            <head>TO THE COMMON-WEALTH of <hi>ENGLAND, William Lilly,</hi> Student in Astro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>logy, wisheth all Prosperity.</head>
            <p>
               <hi>
                  <seg rend="decorInit">G</seg>Od hath granted me to speak, and to conceive as is meet for the things that are given me, it is he that leadeth unto Wisedome, and directeth the wise.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>
               <hi>God hath given me certain knowledge of things that are, to know how the world was made, and the Operation of the Elements.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>
               <hi>The beginning, ending, and midst of the</hi> times, <hi>the alteration of the turning of the Sun, and the</hi> Change <hi>of seasons.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>
               <hi>The Circuits of years, and the Positions of Stars.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>Thus <hi>Salomon</hi> in the seventh of <hi>Wisedom, ver. 15, 16, 17, 18, 19.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>From the sence of these verses it may be in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ferred,
<pb facs="tcp:115088:3"/> that the Science or knowledge of Astrolo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gy, or influences of Heaven are clearly intended, and the Art lawfull, else the wisest amongst mortall men, would not so significantly have mentioned the <hi>Positions</hi> of Stars: for no man can know the <hi>Ope<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rations</hi> and vertues of the Elements except by Astro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>logy; and a <hi>Position,</hi> or figure of <hi>Heaven</hi> is need<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>less, unless from thence a judgement be derived.</p>
            <p>We do confess, that our self emits this present labour in a time wherein we find Astrology much spoken of, much preacht against, much labour taken to over<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>throw it for ever, root and branch; without distinction, or without an <hi>Audite Querelam</hi> of such persons as are therein versed. If our judgement doth vary from others, and that prove offensive, we know as able Divines for learning, yea, more grave, more expe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rimentall in all manner of divinity and Sciences, were of a different judgement concerning the proceeds of this present Parliament, and from those of the late <hi>Synod,</hi> who first took part with this present State; Each maintained their opinions by Scripture, Reason, and Arguments yet there can be but one Truth, there<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore one side or other of these Divines must of necessity have erred, and by their error have seduced many to Destruction.</p>
            <p>Presbitery and Independency are not Twins in uni<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ty, more than <hi>Esau</hi> and <hi>Jacob;</hi> by what we have deli<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vered, we onely say, <hi>severall men, severall opinions:</hi> and <hi>so it will be concerning Astrology;</hi> some main<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>taining its legality, others roaring, and denying it to be a lawfull Art. It shall be our labour to manifest
<pb facs="tcp:115088:3"/> unto Posterity, that as learned Divines as ever lived in this world, have honourably esteem'd Astrology, studied and maintained its lawfulness; nay, those who have been in some places of their Works very bitter enemies unto it, have notwithstanding in other places, acknowledged as much as we desire.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>Augustin</hi> who is so much vaunted of to be an ene<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>my unto this Art, yet thought it no indignity to have knowledge in this Science; but at last concluded, hee would not have a man spend all his life-time in this study. Indeed had he done so, it had been a great loss unto the Church of God.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>Albertus Magnus,</hi> Bishop of <hi>Ratisbon,</hi> whom most admire, and conceive a greater Clerk then <hi>Augustin,</hi> he saith; <hi>Quid desideratius concionatori quam ha<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bere eam scientiam quae doceat nos qualiter mun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>danorum ad hoc, &amp; ad illud mutatio, celestium cor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>porum fiat mutatione.</hi> And immediatly after; <hi>Uni<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>versi ordinationem nulla scientia humana perfectè attingit, sicut Scientia judiciorum Astrorum.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>What is more to be desired by any Preacher, than to know that Science which instructeth us how the change and alteration of worldly affairs come to be thus, or thus disposed by mutation of the Heavenly bodies.</p>
            <p>No humane Science or learning doth perfectly at<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tain the Ordination of the whole Universe; except the knowledge of the judgement of the Starres. <hi>Alber<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tus Mag. tom. 5. pag. 659. Nos habemus unam Sci<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>entiam Mathematicam, que docet nos in rerum cau<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>sis causationem causarum considerare.</hi> Wee have one
<pb facs="tcp:115088:4"/> Mathematicall Science, which teacheth us to consider the causation of causes, in the causes of things.</p>
            <p>Great are the outcrys, and very grievous the censures, wherwith the Ignorant or unknowing man doth at this time burthen <hi>Judiciall Astrology,</hi> and its harm<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>less Professors. Whilst they doe suppose that we <hi>Chri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>stian Astrologers</hi> maintain a fatall necessity of all actions, or as if that God had prescribed good or evill, yea wicked actions unto man. Some of these opinions perhaps were held by <hi>Heathens,</hi> we profess in the fear of God that <hi>Christian Astrology</hi> renounces all such <hi>Atheisme. Nunquam vereundiores nos esse oportet, quam cum de futuris conjicimus,</hi> viz. Let us be modest in our Conjectures of Contingencies, Divines affirm <hi>Adam, Moses</hi> and <hi>Salomon</hi> well versed in Astrology, and <hi>Pineda lib. 3. de rebus Salomon: cap. 8.</hi> saith, <hi>illum judiciariam Astrolo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>giam calluisse circa naturalia, circa inclinationes hominum,</hi> &amp;c. That he well understood <hi>Judiciall Astrology</hi> concerning naturall things, and the in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>clinations of men. It was not the least honour done to <hi>Astrologers,</hi> that the first fruits of the <hi>Gentiles</hi> were men Scient in <hi>Astrology,</hi> who came to worship Christ in the Cradle.</p>
            <p>Whereupon <hi>Gregory</hi> the Great sayes, <hi>Deus ac<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cōmodatè ad eorum scientiam docuit, ut qui in stel<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>larum observatione versabantur, ex stellis Christum discerent,</hi> very fitly did God enable the knowledge of those wise men, that they should learn Christ from the Stars, who were versed in the observation of them. But ahlas, Dean <hi>Owen</hi> of <hi>Christ Church</hi> in
<pb facs="tcp:115088:4"/>
               <hi>Oxford,</hi> will have Astrology to be Diabolicall: <hi>ipse Dixit.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>I ran counter his judgment with the opinion of <hi>Pa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>normitan</hi> an Abbot, an Abbot being an Ace above a Dean. <hi>Astrologia nec per jus Canonicum, nec per Civile est prohibita, nec est in se mala, cum sit una ex artibus liberalibus, &amp; jura praemient has scien<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tias excercentes. Modo non dicant Astrologi ne<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cessitari homines à corporibus Caelestibus.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>Astrology is not prohibited either by the Cannon or Civill Law, nor in it self is evill, sith its one of the liberall Sciences, and men reward those exercising these Sciences; so that Astrologers maintain not, that men are necessitated to this or that from the Celestiall bodies, <hi>Panormitan super 5. Decret. de sorti legi Is.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>
               <hi>Alii &amp; alii planetae diversas complexiones &amp; ha<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bitus &amp; dispositiones in nobis constituunt. Damas<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cen. lib. 2. cap. 7.</hi> These and these Planets doe cause or constitute divers complexions, habits and dispo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>sitions in us.</p>
            <p>I forbear the opinion and high esteem Master <hi>Gre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gory,</hi> and my Countryman <hi>Burton</hi> (men of singular learning) had of Astrology, both these of Dean <hi>Owens</hi> Colledge, but these were profound Schollers. Next Mr. <hi>Nye,</hi> also, a subtill man, he will have Astro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>logy Diabolicall; Ile answer him with the opinion of <hi>Causinus</hi> a Jesuit, who saith, <hi>Certissimum est, cor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pora Caelestia in haec inferiora agere non secus ac Sol &amp; Luna, quorum mirabiles effectus in univer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>sa, quotidie natura experimur:</hi> It is most certain, the heavenly bodies have influence on our inferior
<pb facs="tcp:115088:5"/> bodies, even as the Sun and Moon, whose wonderfull effects upon the whole Universe, we daily find by ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>perience. Where the Question is not Controversiall, I hold a Papists judgment as good and sound as a Protestants. Nay, I will produce a Saint, viz. <hi>Thomas Aquinas 1 part. q. 115.</hi> Who confesseth: <hi>Astrologos in pluribus posse non falsa praedicere, maximè qui<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dem in Communi, quia plures hominum sequun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tur passiones, ad quas cooperari possunt corpora Caelestia.</hi> &amp;c. Astrologers in many things erre not, chiefly in generall matters, because most men follow their passions, unto which the heavenly bodies coope<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rate, <hi>Zanchius</hi> we know is in high esteem with all Protestants, and in some things is against Astrology: treating thereof he makes two questions.</p>
            <p n="1">
               <hi>1. An aliqua futurarum rerum ex astris praesen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>sio ac Divinatio haberi possit, viz.</hi> If any foreknow<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ledge or Divination could bee had of future events from the Stars: himself resolves it thus.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>Nemini enim dubium esse credo, aliquam aliqua<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rum futurarum rerum praesensionem, eamque veram ex astris, seu ex Coelorum influxibus observatis ha<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>beri posse: quandoquidem &amp; Medici ex praecog<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nita futura Lunae mutatione, &amp; ex novi-Lunio, ex pleni-Lunio,</hi> &amp;c. <hi>Verè &amp; certò praedicunt corpo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rum aegrotantium alterationes, morborum incre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>menta, pericula mortis aegrotantibus imminere. Et navium gubernatores ex notatis astris, certò prae<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dicunt ventorum mutationes, maris aestus &amp; alia quam plurima.</hi> I beleeve no man doubts, but that there is some prescience of some future matters, to
<pb facs="tcp:115088:5"/> be made, and that very certain and true from the Starres, and the experimented influxes of the Heavens: wee know Phisitians from the fore<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>knowledge of the Moons Mutation, viz. New and full Moon do TRULY and CERTANLY, foretell the alterations of sick bodyes, the increases of Diseases, &amp; when perill of Death is at hand to the sick.</p>
            <p>All this while <hi>Zanchius</hi> sayth not, <hi>Astrology</hi> is Diabolicall.</p>
            <p>And again, <hi>Voluntas non regenita quandam habet connexionem cum Coelis, quatenus scilicet carna<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>les affectiones,</hi> &amp;c.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>Corporum autem qualitates à coelorum influxi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bus non parum dependent,</hi> &amp;c.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>Voluntas non renata quodam modo in suis actio<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nibus à coelorum influxibus movetur,</hi> &amp;c.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>Quaedam verò sunt, quae certam &amp; plerun{que} ne<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cessariam cum coelis &amp; astris habent connexionem, uti sunt res, actiones{que} omnes in mundo, quae nullo pacto à voluntate proficiscuntur, ver. gra. aut sterilitas aut fertilitas terrae aëris perturbationes, pe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>stis, elementorum commotiones, terrae motus, &amp; alia id genus. Haec enim ex caelestibus influxibus &amp; elementorum quae vi syderum aguntur, commo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tione, magna ex parte eveniunt: ideoque cum astris</hi> certam &amp; plerumque necessariam habent connex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ionem, <hi>dico plerumque; quoniam aliquando eti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>am immediatè à Deo haec immittuntur, citra caelo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rum influxum ut patet in Scripturis;</hi> In English thus: The Will which is not new born, hath a certain connexion with the heavens, even as our Carnall affections have;</p>
            <pb facs="tcp:115088:6"/>
            <p>For the qualities of bodyes doe not a little depend from the influence of the Heavens.</p>
            <p>The unregenerate Will is after a manner moved in its actions, by the influence of the Starrs.</p>
            <p>Some other things there are, which have a certain, and for the most part necessary connexion with the heavens and starres, which no manner of wayes are derived from the Will, <hi>viz.</hi> Dearth or Plenty, per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>turbations of the ayr, the Plague, Commotions of the Elements, Earthquakes, <hi>&amp;c.</hi> All these things doe come to pass, for the most part, from the heavenly influences, and of the Elements which are moved by force and vertue of the Starres, and therefore these have a <hi>certain Commotion,</hi> and for the most part <hi>necessary Connexion</hi> with the starres, I say mostly, for sometimes God doth such things immediatly with<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>out influxes.</p>
            <p>You shall hear what <hi>Scotus</hi> in his <hi>2. Sent. dist. 4. Astra inclinant voluntatem, in nullo tamen necessi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tatur. Accidit tamen frequenter Astrologos vera prognosticare de moribus hominum, propter pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nitatem eorum, ad sequendum appetitivum sensi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tivum.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>The Starrs incline the Will, but in no wise necessi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tate it, Frequently it comes to pass that <hi>Astrologers</hi> foretell <gap reason="illegible" resp="#murp" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>ruths concerning the manner of men, by rea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>son of their proneness to follow their sensitive appetite.</p>
            <p>Again, in <hi>lib. secund. de generat. Hoc modo etiam innotescit, quod qui sciret virtutem signorum, &amp; stellarum in eis positarum dum nascitur res ali<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>qua, posset prognosticari de tota vita rei generatae, licet hoc necessitatem non poneret, quia posset im<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pediri per accidens.</hi>
            </p>
            <pb facs="tcp:115088:6"/>
            <p>By this means it comes to pass, that he who knows the vertues of the Signes and the Planets therein placed, may foretell (if he know when any creature is born) of the whole life of it. So far <hi>Scotus.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>
               <hi>Videmus enim effectus multos hic in terra quo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rum causas ignoramus: beneficio autem verae A<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>strologiae causam suam at originē supra nos in Coe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lis habere cognoscimus. Zanchius, 118. De astrono.</hi> Wee see many effects hear on Earth, whose causes we are ignorant of, yet by benefit of <hi>True Astro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>logie,</hi> wee know they have a cause and production above us in the Heavens.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>Nemo non videt pluvias grandines, nives, maris fluxum &amp; refluxum, ventorum strepitus; sed nemo nisi qui adjutus est beneficio Astrologiae causas eorum in natura positas esse intelligit.</hi> Rains, hayls, snows, ebbing and flowing of the Seas, tem<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pestious winds, no man but by help of <hi>Astrology</hi> can know these, who only understand the causes of these things are in nature. <hi>Hic ergo est usus verae astro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>logiae, ut multorum effectuum qui in terris fiunt causas quae in coelo sunt, agnoscat: aliquando etiam antequam fiunt, ipsos effectus in suis causis prae<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>videat.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>
               <hi>Versatur igitur vera Astrologia circa corpora ce<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lestia &amp; naturales illos effectus qui in corporibus terrenis ex corporum celestium influxu verè &amp; naturaliter fiunt: habet hoc fundamentum prorsus verum: omnia terrena corpora, seu omnia inferiora corpora à coelestibus &amp; superioribus corporibus ali<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>quo modo regi, Zanchius 119. De Astronomia.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>This is therefore the use of true <hi>Astrology,</hi> to un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>derstand
<pb facs="tcp:115088:7"/> from it, the causes which onely are in Hea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ven, of many effects which are on Earth; and some<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>times long before they come to pass, that we may pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vent the effec<gap reason="illegible" resp="#murp" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>s themselves in their causes.</p>
            <p>True <hi>Astrology</hi> therefore is conversant about the heavenly bodyes, and their naturall effects, which have operation upon Earthly bodyes from the influ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ence of the Heavenly, truly and naturally; this hath a <hi>Foundation very true and certain, that all Earthly bodyes, and all inferiour things, in some measure are ordered and disposed by the superiour Celestiall bodyes.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>I will conclude with <hi>Peter Molin, cap. 7. pag. 158.</hi> who in <hi>1640.</hi> Dedicated his Book <hi>De praecogni<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tione,</hi> to the Dean and Chapter of <hi>Canterbury.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>
               <hi>Astrorum quidem est quaedam vis in animos ho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>minum quatenus afficiunt elementa, &amp; per elemen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ta, humores corporum: qui quidem sunt irritamen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ta appetituum sed non afferunt voluntati ullam ne<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cessitatem.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>There is certainly a kind of force or vertue in the Starrs in the minds of men, so farre as the Elements affect them, and by the Elements the humours of bo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dyes are affected; which verily are the stirrers up of the appetites; but these produce not a necessity unto the will: If any <hi>Astrologer</hi> maintain a fatall ne<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cessity, or that the Will is compelled by influence of the Stars, we abhorre his opinion; for we are Christians, and though all Divines urge that point most, there was yet never any one of them produced any one <hi>Astrologer</hi> who maintained fatality; all that ever was objected was onely this piece of a verse of <hi>Mani<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lius;</hi>
               <q>
                  <pb facs="tcp:115088:7"/>Certa stant omnia lege.</q>
            </p>
            <p>This man living in <hi>Augustus</hi> time, and being an Heathen and a Poet, might perhaps mean somewhat else than what is urged against <hi>Astrology,</hi> but again to <hi>Molineus.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>
               <hi>Non est negandum</hi> (saith he) <hi>&amp; caelestia vel aë<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ria ostenta sepe fuisse prenuntia Calamitatum.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>Wee may not deny but that Celestiall or Aëriall prodigies are many times the messengers of Calamity.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>Nec est quisqam nisi cujus animus ab religione plane ob rutuit, qui ad fulmina &amp; fragorem toni<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>truum aut cruenti Cometae aspectum non tangatur metu. Cometem qui dicitur Xiphias portendere bella, experimentis comprobatum est, Pogoniam presignificare mortem regum. Quam ominosa fue<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rit stella crinita 1607. testantur tot calamitates ur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bium, Ecclesiarum projecta Cadavera, 160. pag. Petri Molinei.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>Nor is there any, unlesse such a one who hath no Religion, who is not affrighted at lightning, and crashing of thunder, and the sight of an horrible Co<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>met. A Comet like a Sword, wee find by experience signifies War. A Comet with a Beard portends the death of Kings: How ominous that blazing Star in <hi>16<gap reason="illegible" resp="#murp" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>7.</hi> was, so many calamities of Cities, and de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>solation of Churches well testifies.</p>
            <p>Three severall places of Scripture are produced against us; first, the <hi>18. Deut. 10. verse.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>
               <hi>There shall not be found amongst you, that ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>keth his Son or his Daughter to passe through the
<pb facs="tcp:115088:8"/> fire, or that useth Divination, or an observer of times, or an inchanter, or a witch.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>
               <hi>Causinus</hi> on these words saith thus: <hi>Nimis fa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vent judiciariis qui tam infirmis rationibus impug<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nant. Ubi eum in toto hoc textu sugillantur,</hi> &amp;c.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>Ex quibus constat eos qui tam divinationem exercerint fuisse magos turpes &amp; obscenos, qui nihil cum Astrologis commune habuerunt,</hi> &amp;c.</p>
            <p>The <hi>47.</hi> of <hi>Esay</hi> is urged verse <hi>13. Let now the Astrologers, the Star-gazers and monthly Prog<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nosticators stand up and save them.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>This whole Chapter is against the <hi>Babilonians,</hi> who despising God, and treading his people under foot, were wholly given to superstitious curiosities, and whereas God had determined and said by his Prophets they should come to destruction, these superstitious <hi>Astrologers,</hi> did warrant the contrary; Can the arme of flesh contend with God, or the creature with the Crea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tor; we abhor such things, those <hi>Astrologers</hi> were worthily punished, and so let them be who act such things; yet here is only the abuse not the Art prohi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bited, no more than in those many places of Scripture where God rebukes the Priests: yet they continued them in those times, and wee continue them to this day, they ever were turbulent.</p>
            <p>Jeremy <hi>10.</hi> verse <hi>2. Bee not dismayed at the Signs of Heaven.</hi> What can bee infer'd from hea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ven, but, that the Godly and faithfull who have Di<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vine protection, ought not to fear the Signs or Pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>digies of heaven as the <hi>Heathen</hi> did; what is this unto <hi>Astrology,</hi> those words neither make it lawfull or unlawfull, or are for it or against it, though Master
<pb facs="tcp:115088:8"/>
               <hi>Gattaker</hi> fruitlesly spends a whole side of paper upon these words in his Annotations: but he shall ere long have the judgments of abler Divines than himself and to better purpose on that <hi>2 verse</hi> of <hi>Jeremy. Chap. 10.</hi> You shall hear the exposition of a reverend Minister on this place, equall in years to Mr. <hi>Gataker;</hi> and in true Divinity and knowledge of the Orientall tongues, far surmounting him, his word are th<gap reason="illegible" resp="#murp" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>se.</p>
            <p>The scope and drift of the Prophets word is, that the People of <hi>Israel</hi> should not so stand in awe of the signs of heaven, as the heathen were. For many of the hea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>then looked no higher than the Firmament. They con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>sidered not, that there is an eternall Almighty God ruling over all. God denounced to the <hi>Israelites,</hi> that for their Transgressions, He would make the h<gap reason="illegible" resp="#murp" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>aven over their head to be brasse, and the earth under them to be iron. He would change Natures course, accor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ding to his holy and righteous pleasure. And whereas he will doe so sometimes, His people are not so to feare the Judgements signified in the heaven as doe the Heathen, which know not the God of <hi>Israel,</hi> as if there were no way to escape them.</p>
            <p>Who concludes his Answer with <hi>Osianders</hi> words on the Text: <hi>Ne discatis impietatem gentium, quoe non modo meteora inusitata, &amp; morus syderum ob<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>servant, atque ex iis de futuris eventibus pronunci<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ant, ve um etiam ita metuunt à constellationibus, ut earum effectus evitare non posse existiment. Haec enim Gentium est impietas, nec populum Dei decet. Non damnatur Astrologia pura, (quae nihil habet de magia) si modo quis Astrologicas praedictiones pro conjecturis, non autem pro vaticiniis certis habeat.</hi>
            </p>
            <pb facs="tcp:115088:9"/>
            <p>Learn not the impiety of the Heathens; who did not only observe unusuall meteors and the motions of the Stars, and determined thereby of future Events, but were also so terrified by those Constellations, that they thought it impossible to shun their effects. This was the wickednesse of the <hi>Gentiles,</hi> nor doth it be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>come the people of God so to doe.</p>
            <p>Yet hereby pure <hi>Astrology</hi> is not condemned (so it medles not with unlawfull Magique) or so that it deliver its Astrologicall Predictions for Conjectures, and not maintain them <hi>Oraculous</hi> or <hi>positive.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>We hope now we shall aboundantly satisfie the whole Nation, by the Judgements of such Godly men, whose opinions we have related in our Epistle, and that the people will beleeve <hi>Astrologers</hi> to be Christians, and <hi>Astrology</hi> a lawfull Art, notwithstanding the sense<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>less and scandalous Invectives, corrupt and spurious Expositions daily and weekly delivered by a perverse Generation of men <hi>falsly called Divines.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>Wee conclude with our humble submission to the high Court of Parliament, resolving a full obedience to what Acts shall from thence proceed, either for our encouragement or discouragement, or further progress in <hi>Astrology,</hi> which is so Divine of it self, so usefull for man, and in these last and worst of times was not a little serviceable unto this <hi>Common-wealth.</hi>
            </p>
            <closer>
               <signed>WILLIAM LILLY.</signed>
               <dateline>Corner-House over against Strand-<hi>Bridge,</hi>
                  <date>
                     <hi>March 10. 1651.</hi>
                  </date>
               </dateline>
            </closer>
         </div>
      </front>
      <body>
         <div type="text">
            <pb n="1" facs="tcp:115088:9"/>
            <head>
               <hi>ANNƲS TENEBROSƲS,</hi> OR The Dark Year, 1652. An <hi>Astrologicall</hi> Discourse concerning the ef<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fects of two <hi>Lunar</hi> ECLIPSES, and one formidable one of the SUNNE in this YEAR 1652.</head>
            <p>
               <seg rend="decorInit">I</seg>T was as wisely as truely observed by the learned <hi>Historian Thucydides,</hi> that, some yeares before those three and twenty years <hi>Peloponensian Warres</hi> of the miserable <hi>Greekes</hi> amongst themselves, wherein every <hi>City</hi> or <hi>Commonwealth</hi> of <hi>Greece</hi> was in one kinde or other inga<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ged, <hi>That those things which in former times there went onely a fame of, though rarely in fact confirmed, were then made credible by the ensuing bloody Warres of the</hi> Grecians <hi>one with another. The forerunners of which Quarrels he saith were these; Earthquakes generall to the greatest part of the World,</hi>
               <note place="margin">Thucydides, bi. <hi>1.</hi> pag. <hi>14.</hi>
               </note>
               <hi>and most vio<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lent withall. Eclipses of the</hi> Sunne <hi>oftner then is reported of any for<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mer time, great droughts, &amp;c.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>If we in <hi>Europe,</hi> or many <hi>Kingdomes, People</hi> and <hi>Nations</hi> here<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>in
<pb n="2" facs="tcp:115088:10"/> are hastening unto such disastrous times and accidents as our <hi>Author</hi> delivers unto <hi>Posterity</hi> then to have happened, Let God be glorified, who hath not been wanting in these worst of dayes and times by many <hi>signall Prodigies</hi> so opportunely seene and felt by many men in severall <hi>Countries,</hi> to admo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nish and forewarne even us <hi>English,</hi> as well as many other <hi>Kingdomes</hi> and <hi>Nations</hi> what he intends suddenly to doe. Ve<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ry many and admirable have beene the <hi>Prodigies,</hi> which of late yeares have appeared in the <hi>Dominions</hi> of the King of <hi>Spain;</hi>
               <note place="margin">Insurrection in <hi>Naples</hi> 1647.</note> as first that never to be parallel'd <hi>uproar</hi> and <hi>Tumult</hi> of the People in <hi>Naples</hi> in <hi>July</hi> 1647. at what time they made <hi>Masaniello</hi> a poore <hi>Fisherman</hi> their <hi>Captain Generall,</hi> who for some dayes, had the clearest and absolutest Command over the People, that ever any History mentions, as it is excel<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lently set forth in two little Treatises by the delicate Pen of <hi>James Howell,</hi>
               <abbr>Esq.</abbr>
            </p>
            <p>Another as remarkable a <hi>Prodigie</hi> lately happened in one of the <hi>Countries</hi> belonging to the King of <hi>Spain, viz.</hi> at <hi>Bilbo</hi> in <hi>Biscay,</hi>
               <note place="margin">Inundation waters at <hi>Bil<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bo▪</hi>
               </note> where there was so great an Inundation of Wa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ters, <hi>August</hi> 1651. by reason of a continuall Raine for al<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>most twenty one dayes; during which time the Waters were poured downe from the Mountaines with such vio<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lence, and so mightily increased, that the Waters came six<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>teen foot high into the very <hi>Towne,</hi> to the very great preju<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dice and dammage of al the stranger Merchants and Inhabi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tants. We had the Story thereof in Print, but my selfe had it from the relation of Master <hi>N. Master</hi> of an <hi>English</hi> Ship, and at that time there. Since which time an <hi>English</hi> Mer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>chant there resident, affirmed unto me, that had it not beene for a great strong Church, which partly broke the violence of the Waters as they came down from the Hils, he concei<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ved the Waters would have over-thrown the whole Towne: It is judged three Millions will not repaire the losse that both the Towne and Merchants suffered; and what seemes most Miraculous, is, that one mile below the Towne, the or<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dinary Channell seemed to swell nothing at all with that great aboundance of water which so impetuously tore up
<pb n="3" facs="tcp:115088:10"/> the very Pavements of Stone in the streets, in some places a yard deepe or more. What a fearfull irruption of Waters there happened at <hi>Amsterdam</hi> about <hi>January</hi> or <hi>February</hi> 1650. we all remember, and that People have cause to <hi>Lament.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>These prodigious <hi>Tumults,</hi> and more then ordinary swel<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lings of the Sea-bankes, and furious <hi>Inundations</hi> of <hi>Waters</hi> are most assured <hi>Messengers</hi> of <hi>Gods</hi> wrath and anger unto Man<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>kinde; we all know the <hi>Ʋniversall Deluge</hi> and almost whole drowning of all Mankinde did immediately succeed after the <hi>Cataracts</hi> of Heaven were let loose; you shall onely hear the opinion of two or three learned <hi>Authors</hi> what is the na<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>turall signification of such extraordinary effl<gap reason="illegible" resp="#murp" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>xions of Wa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ters, or other excursion of any one of the Elements. <hi>Inun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dationes maris ac fluminum cum fuerint praeter naturam, populorum &amp; gentium hostilium adventum praenuntiant; si obruant agres,</hi>
               <note place="margin">Cardanus, lib. <hi>14.</hi> devarietat. pag <hi>703.</hi>
               </note>
               <hi>deprae<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dabuntur finitima, &amp; agros ipsos, si maenia sternant, dirum est.</hi> The overflowings of the Sea or of Rivers, when they exceed the ordinary course of nature, doe foretell the comming in or an inrode of People and Strangers, Enemies, into those parts. If these Inundations doe over-whelme the Fields or Pastures, then the bordering places shall be invaded, yea and the Fields themselves; if they levell those Bankes, it is omi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nous. <hi>Multitudo quoque aquarum generaliter morbos portendit, ut etiam medici affirmant.</hi> A multitude of Wat<gap reason="illegible" resp="#murp" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>rs generally be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tokens Diseases. <hi>De aquarum inundationibus atque effluxibus, no<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ta est vox sacrarum literarum. Aquae multae Populi multi.</hi> Concer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ning the inundations and over-flowings of Waters, it is well known what the letter of Scripture saith, <hi>Many Waters, many People. <hi>Salvum me fac Deus, inquit</hi>
               </hi> David, <hi>quoniam aquae ingressae sunt usque ad animam meam.</hi> Save me, O God, saith <hi>David,</hi> because the waters are even entred into my soule. He implies hereby himselfe almost over-pressed by a multitude of enemies. <hi>Nec effusas unquam impunè intumuisse aquas,</hi>
               <note place="margin">Peucerus de Meteorologia, page <hi>338.</hi>
               </note>
               <hi>aut fru<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>stra ventes insolentiore tumultu increpitasse, suis nullae non gentes ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>perimentis, moxque insecutis cladibus didicerunt, etiam nostra, imo recentissima memoria, incursionibus peregrinorum excercituum, di<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>reptionihus, incendiis, coede vastatis omnibus.</hi>
            </p>
            <pb n="4" facs="tcp:115088:11"/>
            <p>Nor have the Waters or Seas at any time to no purpose thus swelled or overflowed their Bankes, or the Windes so impetuously or boysterously roared; very few are the People or <hi>Nations</hi> where such horrible and unusuall <hi>Irruptions</hi> have appeared,<note place="margin">Note.</note> but they have learned by wofull <hi>Experience,</hi> that not many yeares after these outragious <hi>Swellings</hi> the People of that <hi>Nation</hi> where these were, have miserably smarted with immediate succeeding mischiefs, viz. <hi>Either the incursions of Strangers Forces, Armies,</hi> or the like, <hi>into their Countries;</hi> or else a great decay, consumption or wasting of their Men, to<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gether with bloodshed and other wofull calamities conco<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mitant. Of which <hi>Prodigious</hi> irruption then happening, and some Aeriall fights or <hi>Prodi<gap reason="illegible" resp="#murp" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>ies</hi> lately seene in the <hi>States Do<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>minions,</hi> I meane in the <hi>Hollanders,</hi> that prudentiall People will, I hope take speciall notice, it concerning both <hi>Holland</hi> and <hi>Zealand</hi> so to doe, and in a greater measure the Rulers or <hi>Governors</hi> of those <hi>Provinces, Townes</hi> or <hi>Cities</hi> therein sea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ted: For, <hi>Inundatio res est sinistra, malique ominis.</hi> These Inun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dations are il signes, and portend no good unto them. <hi>Parti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>culares enim excessus elementorum irae divinae sunt quaedam praecipua instrumenta, quod se vi summa atque praecipiti effundunt latius.</hi> The particular excesses of the Elements, are certaine principall Engins of Divine vengeance, in regard they extend themselvs with so much force &amp; so great violence more then ordinary. All Philosophers unanimously consenting in this; that, <hi>Ele<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mentorum praedominia vel insignis alicujus inter primas qualitates excessus aut vitia, promiscuè sequitur aliud flagelli genus, quo mor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>talium plurimi perierunt; sames scilicet ac memoranda sterilitas.</hi> Cor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nelius Gemma <hi>de Naturae divinis Caracterismis,</hi> pag. 170.</p>
            <p>The <hi>Masteries</hi> or over-powring of the Elements, or any famous or unusuall extravagancies or excesses of any of them amongst themselves or their first qualities, doe mani<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fest, that not long after promiscuously there followes a kind of <hi>Scourge,</hi> whereby many People are consumed; and this is usually <hi>Famine</hi> or some remarkable <hi>Barrennesse of the Earth.</hi> The overflowing of the watery Element hath ever beene re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>puted Prodigious unto the People where it happened.<note place="margin">Let <hi>Amster<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dam</hi> beware.</note>
               <hi>Aqua<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rum
<pb n="5" facs="tcp:115088:11"/> vero irruptio potius ad vulgus ignobile spectat; agunt enim aquae multitudine &amp; impetu: Aquarum gurges inevitabilis, qui nullis ob<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>jicibus, nulla vel arte deinceps vel violentia coercetur, quin pariter omnia, permistis inter se arenis, saxis, cinere, fumo, igne &amp; aqua, in Chaos teterrimum prolabuntur,</hi> Gemma 180.</p>
            <p>The irruption, overflowing or breaking forth of Waters most concernes the common People or ignoble person; for Waters doe work with fiercenesse and violence: The Whirl<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>poole or violence of Waters is inevitable, nor is its force or whirling restrained or kept in by any Gin or Device of Art; but all alike, and together both <hi>Sands, Stone, Gravell, Cin<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ders,</hi>
               <note place="margin">What the States of <hi>Hol<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>land</hi> may ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pect from their People.</note>
               <hi>Smoake</hi> or <hi>Vapour</hi> are all gathered together into a most horrible <hi>Chaos;</hi> intimating hereby, that such like watery <hi>Prodigies,</hi> doe declare an unruly Multitude and giddy Peo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ple, that would willingly let loose the raines of <hi>Government,</hi> and become disobedient unto <hi>Authority,</hi> though in the end it turne unto their owne <hi>Confusion,</hi> and also <hi>Destruction</hi> of all those who participate with them in their folly and Coun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cell. <hi>Igitur si laxato naturae Nodo, convulsisque claustris extra suos limites aquae proferantur, &amp; effraeni violentiae impetu terram pera<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>grent, non id temerè fortuitoque, sed divino fit imperio: tum ut gra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vem puniendis hominum sceleribus stragem edant: tum ut in poste<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rum arma hostium, &amp; intestinos praecipuè factionum motus, pe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>st<gap reason="illegible" resp="#murp" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>mque &amp; famem terris ingruentem praenuntient,</hi> Eden Nehusus <hi>lib.</hi> 20. <hi>pag.</hi> 180.</p>
            <p>If therefore the chaine of Nature be unloosed, and the en<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>closures of Waters pluckt up, so that they get forth of their owne proper Channels or Bounds, and overflow the <hi>Earth</hi> or ground with a lawlesse mastery of violence; this is not done by <hi>Fortune</hi> or <hi>chance,</hi> but it comes to passe by <hi>Divine command.</hi> That People may be as well sensible of some fear<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>full slaughters at hand for punishing the wretchednesse of men, as of Factions, <hi>intestine Divisions, Armies of Enemies,</hi> a <hi>Plague</hi> and <hi>Famine</hi> to be approaching, &amp;c. But of this enough.</p>
            <p>Let us come neerer home; for the most of what hath yet beene delivered concernes the <hi>Spaniard</hi> and <hi>Dutch,</hi> and in
<pb n="6" facs="tcp:115088:12"/> some measure the <hi>French.</hi> And although we in our ensuing Discourse, intended at first onely a discovery of the <hi>naturall significations</hi> of three <hi>Eclipses</hi> in this yeare 1652. yet occasio<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nally let me leave this <hi>Memorandum</hi> unto <hi>Posterity,</hi> of some <hi>Prodigies</hi> which our Nation are fully satisfied to have beene seene in <hi>England;</hi> we cannot deny but that in every of the years 1644. 1645. 1646. 1647. in severall <hi>Counties</hi> of <hi>Eng<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>land</hi> there were more frequently then in former times seene <hi>Parelia</hi> or <hi>Mock suns,</hi> or <hi>Paraselenes</hi> or <hi>Mock-Moones,</hi> besides two dayes before that fatall Fight at <hi>Marston Moore</hi> in <hi>York<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>shire, July</hi> 1644. our selves and thousands more beheld strange <hi>apparitions, clashings, fightings</hi> in the Ayre from about eight or nine of clock at night until about eleven or twelve, with monstrous shapes in the Ayre and strange <hi>Hiatus</hi> ga<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pings or openings of the Clouds.<note place="margin">Rigel, Apho. <hi>87.</hi>
               </note>
               <hi>Signa quae videntur in coelo, quae apparuerint extra motum &amp; cursum naturae, nunquam eveniunt sine magna mutatione Regnorum illius climatis in quo apparuerint.</hi>
               <note place="margin">Two dayes after these apparitions <hi>Don Rupert</hi> was routed at <hi>Marston</hi> in <hi>Yorkshire.</hi>
               </note>
               <hi>Signes</hi> or <hi>apparitions</hi> which are seen in Heaven, and doe ap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>peare without motion and against the course of nature, such <hi>Prodigies</hi> as these never appeare unto Men without a great <hi>change</hi> or <hi>Mutation</hi> of the Kingdomes of that <hi>climate</hi> in which they were visible.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>Plures soles ferè visos constat, cum nova essent foedera consuta, aut structae adornataeque conspirationes,</hi>
               <note place="margin">Peucerus, lib. Meteorolog. pag. <hi>340.</hi>
               </note>
               <hi>vel ad rapienda imperia, vel eos qui praesederint de fastigio dejicendos: aut omnino, nisi aliqui res no<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vas molirentur, à quibus impenderent innovationes turbationésque e<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tiam in Religione.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>Its manifest, many <hi>Suns</hi> are then seene, when new <hi>Leagues</hi> should be patcht up, and specious conspiracies layd or de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>signed,<note place="margin">No Prodigy but hath some signification as unto the Religious.</note> either to bereave some of their <hi>Dominions,</hi> or to pull downe some <hi>Great ones,</hi> who then doe governe with scorne and disgrace; either such things happen altogether, or else there is much disturbance and innovation in <hi>Religion</hi> or things <hi>Divine.</hi> That such like accidents have succeeded in <hi>England</hi> of late, and in <hi>Scotland</hi> and <hi>Ireland,</hi> no <hi>Criticke</hi> dares deny it: I could verifie <hi>Peucers</hi> words by examples drawne from other <hi>Countries.</hi>
            </p>
            <pb n="7" facs="tcp:115088:12"/>
            <p>But the subject of our Pen,<note place="margin">Of the three Eclipses 1652</note> is onely three <hi>Eclipses</hi> of this Year 1652. <hi>Viz.</hi> two of the <hi>Moone</hi> and one of the <hi>Sunne,</hi> a very <hi>Memorable</hi> one; at which I beleeve <hi>Ambrose Merlin</hi> hin<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ted, when in one of his <hi>Brittish Prophesies,</hi> mentioning the year 1652. he cals it <hi>A Darke Yeare;</hi>
               <note place="margin">
                  <hi>Merlin</hi> cals 1652. a darke year.</note> which he might ve<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ry well do, in regard the first <hi>Eclips</hi> of the <hi>Moone,</hi> the fifteenth of <hi>March,</hi> there will be almost <hi>ten digits Eclipsed;</hi> two digits more had made a <hi>totall obscuration;</hi> and in that of the Sunne the twenty ninth day of <hi>March,</hi> there will be eleven di<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gits and fifty five minutes Eclipsed as Captain <hi>George Whar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ton</hi> hath acurately and learnedly delivers in his <hi>Hemero<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>scopeion.</hi>
               <note place="margin">Captain <hi>Whar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ton</hi> an excel<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lent Calcula<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tor.</note>
            </p>
            <p>The third <hi>Eclips</hi> of the <hi>Moon</hi> will be visible the seventh day of <hi>September,</hi> the <hi>Digits</hi> there eclipsed will be neare ten.</p>
            <p>The magnitude of these <hi>Eclipses,</hi> and the many great a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ctions likely to succeed after them, will occasion <hi>Admira<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion</hi> all over <hi>Europe;</hi> and therefore I conceive <hi>Eickstadius</hi> when he came to give the calculation of them in his <hi>Ephe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>merides,</hi> breakes out into these words: <hi>Propter infrequentiam formidandae: These Eclipses</hi> (saith he) <hi>for their infrequency are much to be feared.</hi> And indeed the effects hereof, or from hence, will be formidable; which onely, besides some private re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>quests, have occasioned our pen to assume both liberty to write, and freedome of our sence in its own expression, that we might thereby largely expatiate our thoughts having so copious but very unfrequent an Argument for our <hi>Basis;</hi> verily, it was long ere we were willing to assume this la<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bour, which we declined untill towards the beginning of <hi>February;</hi> but then not knowing of any other Pen which would undertake the burthen or tediousnesse of the sub<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ject, we at last mustered up our forces, and at such spare houres as we gained from our daily imployment, have pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>duced the <hi>Treatise ensuing;</hi> for <hi>Providence</hi> hath already brought us on the Stage of this World, and made us sensible that many of our Endevours formerly published have received a candid and gratefull acceptance amongst the learned in all
<pb n="8" facs="tcp:115088:13"/> parts of <hi>Europe,</hi>
               <note place="margin">
                  <p>A scandalous exposition on the second ver. of the 10. Chapt. of <hi>Iere<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>miah</hi> by <hi>T. G,</hi> hinting in ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>presse termes the Author of this Discours; but, <hi>Senes bis pucri.</hi>
                  </p>
                  <p>The Author begins from a certain <hi>Epoche</hi>
                  </p>
               </note> notwithstanding the <hi>Malevolent Detractions</hi> of <hi>Home-borne Antagonists,</hi> who have both lost their Oyle and reputation, by endeavoring a confutation of what they un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>derstood not, having over-lookt our <hi>Labours</hi> with <hi>uncircum<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cised</hi> affections and <hi>Presbyterian Charity,</hi> most absurdly abu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>sing their better time in <hi>Criticismes</hi> and fruitlesse <hi>Expositions</hi> on <hi>Texts</hi> of <hi>Scripture,</hi> against the whole current of Antiqui<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ty, Reason and very genuine sence of the <hi>Words themselves.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>But that we may begin our worke from some certaine <hi>E<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>poche</hi> of Time, and not involve our selves into a laborinth of unnecessary <hi>Inquiries,</hi> we are to consider that, <hi>Nullus ef<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fectus sive parvus à Revolutione vel ab aliis significantibus erit, quod non primum a Radice habeat Exordium: Ludovicus de Rigiis,</hi> Aphoris. 51. <hi>Quare summa diligentia radices considerandae sunt; viz.</hi> There is no effect or materiall accident, no matter though it seeme small, which is signified either in a <hi>Revoluti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on</hi> or otherwise, which first of all had not a <hi>Beginning</hi> from some Radix; therefore with great diligence, the first <hi>Roots</hi> or foundations of things are to be inquired into.</p>
            <p>
               <note place="margin">♂ ♄ &amp; ♃ 1603.</note>In our <hi>Inquirie</hi> we finde that in the yeare 1603. and the seventh of <hi>December,</hi> there was a <hi>Mutation</hi> of the two superi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>or or Planets, <hi>Saturne</hi> and <hi>Jupiter</hi> out of the watery <hi>Triplicitie</hi> into the <hi>Fiery Trigon.</hi>
               <note place="margin">Fiery Trigon.</note>
               <hi>Saturnus &amp; Jupiter mutant res &amp; conver<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tunt, eritque variationis initium cum mutantur de una triplicitate ad aliam in conjunctionibus, &amp; ex una figura in aliam.</hi> Rigel. Apho. 127. <hi>Cardanus</hi> will have us beleeve that there are very ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ny means and wayes in <hi>Astrology</hi> whereby we may give judg<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment of the great <hi>Mutations</hi> contingent in this World; but out <hi>Author</hi> tels us, That <hi>Saturne</hi> and <hi>Jupiter</hi> doe change and overturne many humain affaires in this World, and that then or near that time there is first an appearance of them, when <hi>Jupiter</hi> and <hi>Saturn</hi> doe change from one Triplicity in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>to another in their meetings or conjunctions, or from one <hi>Figure</hi> or <hi>Forme</hi> unto another. <hi>Saturn</hi> and <hi>Jupiter</hi> had conti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nued very neare two hundred years in, the watery Triplici<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ty, but now they have left that <hi>Trigon,</hi> and will continue as long in the fiery: as water and fire are contraries, so will the
<pb n="9" facs="tcp:115088:13"/> Actions of these almost 180. yeers yet to come, be quite averse to what was then and in those times acted; and that is most rationall, and of especiall concernment for such as will hereafter wade into these mysteries: the same things are directed by <hi>Cardanus,</hi> that subtil Philosopher, in his first <hi>Sect. Apho.</hi> 64. <hi>Considerare oportet Conjunctiones magnas, medias &amp; minores, tum Luminarium, atque etiam mutationes Planetarum tardigradorum in Signis, congressusque ad fixas pro temporum mu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tationibus.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>We ought to consider in our judgements the <hi>Great,</hi>
               <note place="margin">These are in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tended of ♄ ♃ and ♂, of which you may read copiously in our <hi>Propheti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>call Merlin,</hi> printed 1644. 1603.</note>
               <hi>Means</hi> or <hi>Middle</hi> and <hi>Minor Conjunctions,</hi> as also the Conjunctions of the two Luminaries, together with the <hi>Mutations</hi> of the <hi>supe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rior Planets</hi> who are of slow motion, their congresse to the fixed Starres; for these shew the variation and alteration of <hi>Times.</hi> At that moment of time when the preceding Con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>junction of <hi>Saturn</hi> and <hi>Jupiter</hi> was celebrated, and had their first entrance into the fiery <hi>Trigon,</hi> the ninteenth degree of ♎ did culminate; and in that very degree 1605. there was an Eclips of the <hi>Sun</hi> the second of <hi>Octob.</hi> in the afternoone, the digits Eclipsed being ten. What <hi>English</hi> man remembers not the <hi>Powder plot</hi>
               <note place="margin">Powder-Plot.</note> which was to have beene executed the fift of <hi>Novemb.</hi> following, for the Eclips in 1605. was in partill conjunction with the degree <hi>Culminating</hi> at the <hi>Coition</hi> of the two <hi>superiors;</hi> the intention of those Traytors and unad<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vised men being evidently apparant to root up <hi>Authority,</hi> viz. <hi>King, Lords</hi> and <hi>Commons,</hi> who are represented unto us from the tenth House: which horrible Action and to be admi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>red <hi>Accident</hi> happening so soone after the <hi>Change</hi> of <hi>Saturn</hi> and <hi>Jupiter</hi> into the fiery <hi>Trigon,</hi> cals unto my memory and seemes to confirme what <hi>Leovitius</hi> the <hi>Bohemian</hi> wrote 1564.<note place="margin">Of ♄ and ♃ their entrance into the fiery Trygon 1603</note> vnto the <hi>Emperor</hi> concerning the probability of those acti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ons which were likely to happen upon the change of the two superiors out of the <hi>watery</hi> into the <hi>fiery Trigon;</hi> his words are these; <hi>Cum ergo nunc novus Trigonus impendeat qui igneus est, haud dubiè nova secula sequentur quae repentinas &amp; vio<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lentas mutationes inducent.</hi> Seeing now there is a new <hi>Trigon</hi> at hand which is the <hi>fiery Trigon,</hi> without doubt new ages shall
<pb n="10" facs="tcp:115088:14"/> follow, which shall produce sudden, rash and violent chan<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ges in the world.<note place="margin">King <hi>James</hi> his coming in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>to <hi>England.</hi> The Earle of <hi>Northumberl.</hi> a man of great spirit, would have had King <hi>Jam<gap reason="illegible" resp="#murp" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>s</hi> come in upon terms</note> Let one example serve instead of many. That yeare <hi>viz.</hi> 1603. <hi>James</hi> King of <hi>Scotland,</hi> peaceably be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>came King of <hi>England,</hi> but he might thanke a <hi>Cowardly</hi> igno<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ble Nobility for it, who then ruled the rost; old <hi>Northumber<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>land</hi> was of another opinion, being a neer neighbour to the <hi>Scot;</hi> he knew their <hi>Treacheries</hi> and <hi>Beggeries.</hi> There were many eminent mutations upon this grand change of the <hi>Planets</hi> all over <hi>Europe</hi> neer those times in the beginning of this <hi>fiery Trigon;</hi> in truth we are in this Age (and so must be some Ages succeeding) under the dominion of this <hi>fiery Trigon;</hi> and ther fore it is no wonder to me, to see or hear every moment of so great <hi>alterations</hi> in the Kingdoms and Common-wealths of <hi>Europe;</hi> ever and anon we must expect such sudden changes in these our times, as no Age in former time could <hi>parallel;</hi> and these sharp and bitter Contentions are assuredly to have their beginning from <hi>Religious</hi> preten<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ces, or breach of <hi>Customes:</hi> but alas, Religion in many is but the <hi>Foyl; Self-ends,</hi> next to the <hi>decrees</hi> of <hi>Providence, being the only Incendiary,</hi> and sole cause in every Mutation; one arme of flesh pulling down another, and thus it will be as long as Priests have any hand in temporal affairs or Councels.</p>
            <p>These things, and such actions are wholly of the nature of the <hi>fiery Trigon: Praedominium elementi ignei, ad Reges Civi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tatumque praefectos, rerum quoque publicarum maximos motus desig<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nari;</hi>
               <note place="margin">
                  <hi>Cornelius Gem<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ma,</hi> of the fie<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ry Trigon, or fiery Element</note>
               <hi>praecipuè vero seditiones populi, quanquam &amp; mutationes legum magna ex parte subsequuntur.</hi> The Praedominion of the <hi>fiery Element</hi> having influence over men, doth design accidents to ensue unto Kings, Rulers of Commonwealths and Cities; especiall relation it hath in manifesting the seditions or uproars of people; yet ever these things are accompanied with the change of Customes, Lawes, and Ceremonies in Religion, with Schisms, Heresies, &amp;c. all prodigies end in Schisms.</p>
            <p>These things we have handled occasionally; but seeing an Eclipse in <hi>Aries</hi> is intended for the subject matter of our Discourse, let us review Antiquity and its monuments, and
<pb n="11" facs="tcp:115088:14"/> thereby we shall discover what were those <hi>mutations,</hi> what those <hi>Catastrophes</hi> which formerly were concomitant upon either Solar or Lunar Eclipse in <hi>Aries.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>In <hi>anno Dom.</hi> 1418, there was an Eclipse in <hi>Aries,</hi> viz. 26. degrees, and 6. day of <hi>April.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>And the yeer following, <hi>viz.</hi> 1419. the 26. day of <hi>March,</hi>
               <note place="margin">Leovitius, de magnis Con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>junct<gap reason="illegible" resp="#murp" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>onibus.</note> there was another Eclipse, (<hi>satis tetra,</hi> saith mine Au<gap reason="illegible" resp="#murp" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>hor) a very horrible and great one; after which, Tumults in <hi>Bo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>hemia</hi> succeeded, and many other strange accidents, as the learned and industrious Citizen of <hi>London</hi> Master <hi>Isackson</hi> re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lates in his <hi>Chronology,</hi> called <hi>Saturni Ephemerides,</hi>
               <note place="margin">
                  <hi>Isackson</hi> the Londoner a painful Histo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>riographer.</note> unto whom I refer the Reader.</p>
            <p>In the yeer 1485. an Eclipse of the <hi>Sun</hi> was in the 6. de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gree of <hi>Aries, Quae multa cumulavit mala,</hi> saith <hi>Leovitius,</hi> which stirred up by its sharp influence much wickednesse and many evils Untill 1530. and the 29. of <hi>March,</hi> the very same day our great Eclipse 1652. fals on: I say, that day in the 19. of <hi>Aries,</hi> there was a great Eclipse, <hi>Gubernatore ejus Marte, constituto propè oculum Tauri, stellam fixam violentam ac fervidam;</hi> viz. The <hi>Governour</hi> of that Eclipse was <hi>Mars,</hi>
               <note place="margin">The Buls eye a violent fixed star.</note> and he in <hi>Ge<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mini,</hi> neer that violent and furious star called <hi>the Buls eye,</hi> which is a fixed star, hot, violent, fierce, and of evill influ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ence: Behold what succeeded;<note place="margin">God defend our Gover<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nours, its pos<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>sible some clandestine designe is hatching by such men, and thereby they may run into a praemunire. He promiseth to write the Authors life. ☉ eclipsed in 29. ♈.</note> Then did the noble City of <hi>Florence</hi> learn subjection, <hi>the Clergy of</hi> England <hi>did then run in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>to a praemunire;</hi> for no premonition will incline these people to <hi>subjection; &amp; hoc est certum &amp; probatum per Kit Love,</hi> and <hi>his dear Brethren and Fellow-Petitioners:</hi> Not a treason can be man<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>aged without a Priest; but how <hi>Leonard Cook</hi> of <hi>Islington</hi> came to be one of that Fraternity of Petitioners, I much won<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>der, he being <hi>ab Infantia, homo rudis, Agrestisque &amp; minimi ingenii.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>We draw neerer unto the present times, in <hi>anno</hi> 1567. and 9. of <hi>April,</hi> there was an Eclips of <hi>Sol</hi> in 29. degr. of <hi>Aries,</hi> and this obscuration of <hi>Sol</hi> so great, that <hi>Leovitius</hi> cryed out, <hi>Profectò tam tetram ac horrendam Eclipsin Solis ab anno Dom.</hi> 1544. <hi>non habuimus, nec etiam multis futuris saeculis habituri su<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mus.</hi> Verily such a terrible and horrid Eclipse of the <hi>Sun</hi> we
<pb n="12" facs="tcp:115088:15"/> have not had, saith our Author, since 1544. nor in many Ages succeeding shall have the like: whereupon he bursts out into these words, <hi>Mihi summi Magistratus periculum exilii aut captivitatis ostendi videtur.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>In my judgement (quoth he) here is intended either the banishment of some great Prince or Governour, or some wofull calamity unto the Magistracy. <hi>Like presidents produce like actions,</hi> and like examples may happen to severall <hi>Ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gistrates</hi> in <hi>Europe</hi> upon the influence of our present great Eclipse.<note place="margin">A Scottish King murthe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>red about 1567.</note> At that time you shall finde a <hi>Scotch King</hi> murther<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed, a matter of no great moment in <hi>Scotland;</hi> God grant those whom our Commonwealth shall send over into <hi>Scot<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>land</hi> for Governours, be not served so really; such a thing I fear will be endeavoured; <hi>for once a Scot, and ever a Scot:</hi> The <hi>Hollander</hi> (for under them and there,<note place="margin">Upon a for<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mer eclips in ♈ the <hi>Hollan<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ders</hi> molested.</note> I intend the <hi>Ʋnited Provinces</hi>) was extreamly afflicted by the <hi>Spaniard,</hi> the Duke of <hi>Alva</hi> then entring those Countryes, and building that magnificent <hi>Cittadell</hi> at <hi>Antwerp,</hi> to bridle that wealthy City. If the present <hi>Hollander</hi> urge their Neighbour Nations too far, they may happily taste the force of another <hi>Forreigner,</hi> no lesse powerfull then <hi>Alva,</hi> and be made sensible of an In<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vasion to better purpose then that of <hi>Alva.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>From the yeer 1567. untill 1614. there was no conspicu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ous or memorable Eclipse in the Sign <hi>Aries,</hi> but then in 1614 there was one of the <hi>Sun</hi> in 19. degr. and 9. min. of <hi>Aries,</hi> but it was not visible in our Horizon, and so not in our Cognizance.</p>
            <p>In 1633. there was a moderate Eclipse in 18. degr. and 21. min. of <hi>Aries,</hi> the digits eclipsed onely five, although a petty eclipse, yet being in <hi>Aries,</hi> the effects which attended it were many and memorable, both in <hi>England</hi> and <hi>Germany;</hi> neer unto that time you will finde wofull calamities to be stirring in <hi>Germany,</hi> and the people in <hi>England</hi> generally in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>clining to dislike of the Kings <hi>actions</hi> and <hi>Councels,</hi> matters, things; Councels then drawing unto maturity both in <hi>Eng<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>land</hi> and <hi>Scotland.</hi>
            </p>
            <div type="account">
               <pb n="13" facs="tcp:115088:15"/>
               <head>Of the first <hi>ECLIPSE</hi> of the <hi>MOON,</hi> visi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ble in <hi>ENGLAND</hi> the <hi>15.</hi> of <hi>March,</hi> being Munday <hi>1651/2.</hi> at <hi>4.</hi> of the clock <hi>4.</hi> min. <hi>A. M.</hi>
                  <figure>
                     <figDesc>astrological chart</figDesc>
                  </figure>
               </head>
               <p>WE find in the beginning of this Eclipse, the <hi>Luminary</hi> eclipsed, <hi>viz.</hi> the <hi>Moon,</hi> to be descending from the ninth house, hastening into the eighth, in which she is un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>till almost her greatest obscuration; towards, or at the end
<pb n="14" facs="tcp:115088:16"/> of her eclipse, she fals even to the cusp of the seventh, and so under the Earth. If from thence we inferre this rationall Judgement, That there is a People yet in being, and they pretending unto Godlinesse or Religion, which men we in our plaine <hi>English</hi> doe call Divines, Ministers, Preachers, Ecclesiasticall Men,<note place="margin">Probable Acti<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>ons to ensue after this Eclips.</note> or men conversant in holy things; in foraigne parts they are called Bishops, Cardinals, Abbots, Munks, Friers &amp;c. Men that step up sometimes into Pul<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pits, and pretend to instruct our Soules with the Doctrine of Christanity, but obedience to their owne Constitutions; I say, if from hence we deliver this probable Judgement; <hi>That there are yet left a generation</hi> of such Men, who are now privately designing some future trouble unto our <hi>State</hi> and those <hi>Commonwealths</hi> where otherwise they reside, which will againe occasion the drawing of blood unto our State and other Nations, and destruction unto themselves, <hi>viz.</hi> Mini<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>stery and Munkeries, and unto as many of their abused Dis<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ciples and Proselytes, as shall suffer themselves to be over<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ruled or deceived by their treasonable Councell: I erre not, and therefore I hope the World will cleer me, that I doe not abuse or so much as once name or mention the <hi>Presbyterians</hi> or their <hi>Proselytes.</hi> It is the Judgement of <hi>Cardan Seg.</hi> 5. <hi>Aph.</hi> 56.<note place="margin">The begining of ♎ ill.</note>
                  <hi>Initium Arietis per se bonum est; turbulentum autem &amp; ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lum librae initium.</hi> This <hi>Lunar Eclips</hi> is in the beginning of the signe <hi>Libra,</hi> which <hi>Cardan</hi> affirmes to be turbulent and evill; and in regard part of its greatest obscuration fals to be neer or fully in the seventh House, without doubt its the forerunner of many tumults, desperate designes, which will not terminate but in blood and ruine of those who first contrived and afterwards shall dare to execute them, or put them into Act.</p>
               <p>This Eclips is in the middle of that Asterisme which we appropriate to the <hi>Virgin,</hi> over which <hi>Mercury</hi> rules, and it is humane, therefore the Events doe belong unto men. <hi>Asterismorum natura expenditur cum ex signatura; Orig.</hi> 461.</p>
               <p>The nature of the Asterisme wherein the Eclips shall happen, as also its signature must be inquired after; now sith the signe <hi>viz: Libra,</hi> is humane, and the Asterisme also,
<pb n="15" facs="tcp:115088:16"/> it hath much relation unto Mankinde and actions to be per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>formed by Man, as Justice and upright Judgement,<note place="margin">Complaint for Iustice.</note> the want whereof this Eclips doth demonstrate, or its due and full ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ecution. <hi>Supersunt alia etiam, proximè quidem ab ipsis homi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nibus oriunda; ut simultates, inimicitiae, bellorum turbines, quorum parens est Injustitia, dum quisque meum illud ac tuum ita tuetur, ut suae cupiditati nullum constituat modum; imo dum cuique quod suum est, reddere pollicentur, eripiunt meum ac tuum, communia faciunt cuncta, &amp; bonis perpetuo inhiant alienis.</hi> Gemma lib. 1. 171.</p>
               <p>There remaine many things besides, which prove as Engines to stir up men unto wickednesse, <hi>viz.</hi> dissimulati<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ons, emnities, which are the very whirlewinds or stirrers up of Warrs, whose Parent or first occasioner was <hi>Injustice,</hi> whil'st every one doth so defend that which is called <hi>Mine</hi> as if it were <hi>Thine;</hi> yet so as he who pretends to do this gives no restraint to his own covetous desires; nay whilst he or they do promise to give unto every one what is his, they violent<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly take away both <hi>Mine</hi> and <hi>Thine,</hi> or my <hi>Right</hi> and thy <hi>Right;</hi> they make all things common, and still are hanging after other mens estates. Such like things it seems the ge<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nerality of people in <hi>Germany,</hi> the Low <hi>Countries, France</hi> and <hi>England</hi> will speake of, and complaine of: I hope God will be mercifull unto the <hi>English Common-wealth,</hi> and suf<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fer no such cause to remaine amongst us to give so ge<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nerall a distaste, &amp;c. Seeing this Eclips doth happen so neer the Spring, at what time men are preparing the Earth to receive Seeds;<note place="margin">The Spring conceived to be moderate.</note>
                  <hi>De satione &amp; rebus ex terra primùm prodeun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tibus, de arborum fructiferarum pullulatione seu germinibus habet sig<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nificationem, item vitis, ficuum aliorum{que} fructum spe;</hi> as <hi>Origanus</hi> will have it, and reason it selfe, 1461. <hi>Viz.</hi> the signification of this Eclips will have much to doe in such things or Seeds as Men sow neere this time, or put into the Earth, or on such Plants and Trees which doe now put forth themselves ei<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther in sprouting or budding, and these effects, <hi>viz.</hi> either to have unkindely windes or blasts, we must expect, in regard it fals in the very entrance of that season we in <hi>England</hi> vul<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>garly
<pb n="16" facs="tcp:115088:17"/> call the Spring; though for my part I rather conceive the Spring more properly first begins at what time the <hi>Sunne</hi> enters <hi>Capricorne,</hi>
                  <note place="margin">When the Sp<gap reason="illegible" resp="#murp" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>ing pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>perly begins.</note> for that then the Sap of Trees and other Plants does first begin to dilate and ascend upward; the Sun then first beginning to incline from his furthest <hi>South Decli<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nation</hi> towards the <hi>North.</hi> We are also to consider that this signe <hi>Libra</hi> is equinoctiall, and therefore hath signification <hi>De sacris &amp; religionis cultu potissimum, Orig.</hi> 461. Here will be much time consumed (perhaps lost) in discussing things ho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly,<note place="margin">Time spent to no purpose a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bout Ceremo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nies.</note> or of Divine worship, or points of Faith, or Fundamen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tals in Religion.</p>
               <p>It is very true, and we doe judge Religion will be much spoken of, much talked of, many disputes appearing to be about it, during the continuance of the effects of this eclips; for I well remember upon that memorable Eclips in or a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bout the tenth of <hi>January</hi> 1639, the Scottish Nation raised an Army and made for their pretence of warre, <hi>onely an obtrusion upon their Nation of a semipopish Booke or Common pray<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>er Book;</hi>
                  <note place="margin">The <hi>Scots</hi> first angry at the <hi>Common Pray<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>er Booke.</hi>
                  </note> but the sad consequences which after that happened ended not so soon as it began, but in a most wofull distem<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>per of both <hi>England</hi> and <hi>Scotland</hi> in much bloodshed and most fierce warrs: both nations haveing sensibly now been made understand of how dangerous a consequent it is to embroyle our selves into a warre upon the prateing and pretending <hi>Glosses</hi> of those we call Ministers who never care for the welfare of any other sort of People but of their own <hi>Hierarchy,</hi>
                  <note place="margin">Many Mini<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>sters respect themselves onely.</note> that so they might Lord it and domineer like pet<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ty Tyrants over the <hi>Commonalty</hi> and <hi>Gentry.</hi> But if in this E<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>clips we consider either the strength of <hi>Jupiter</hi> or his positi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on, we finde him wholly out of all Dignity either essentiall or accidentall. <hi>A Jove Praelatura,</hi> we have <hi>Jupiter</hi> to signifie <hi>Prelacy</hi> and Ecclesiasticall affaires. [<hi>Baranzanus; sub Jove prin<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cipes, Ecclesiastici, politici, Sacerdotes.</hi> 224. Under <hi>Jupiter</hi> we sig<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nifie Princes, Cardinals, all Ecclesiasticall Potentates, Policy; and <hi>Sacerdotes,</hi> because it ever did, shall passe for Priests.] This Eclips findes them in much sorrow and anguish of minde (the influence of this Eclips crosses their Designes)
<pb n="17" facs="tcp:115088:17"/> they now fearing the downfall of their Tythes,<note place="margin">People unwil<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ling to pay Tythes.</note> and a gene<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rall tergiversation of the people against them in many pla<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ces; the People who begin to see without Spectacles, gene<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rally declining their spurious and seditious Doctrines a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gainst Parlament and State, whether derived from <hi>John Cal<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vin</hi> or the babling of a silly <hi>Scottish Presbytery.</hi>
                  <note place="margin">Ministry threatned all over <hi>Europe.</hi>
                  </note>
               </p>
               <p>Farre be it from me to say that this judgement against <hi>Divines,</hi> shall be onely particular to <hi>England</hi> and <hi>Scotland;</hi> no assuredly; in many places of <hi>Germany, France, Italy</hi> and other Nations there will arise much trouble and affliction unto the whol <hi>Hierarchy</hi> of them, whether <hi>Papist</hi> or <hi>Protestant:</hi> this will generally fall upon them everywhere wheresoever they reside.</p>
               <p>I rather write this with sorrow of heart then any joy or delight to see the downfal of so many men, who, had they improved their talents in Learning and divinity conscien<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tiously for education of those flocks God had commited unto them,<note place="margin">The Authors wel-wishes unto the god<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly Divines.</note> might have expected an other manner of reward from heaven, and a more benigne acceptance of their la<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>bours from men: The great God of Heaven protect the pious and godly Divines of our Nation, for some we have: and let them never want incouragement or a most bounti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>full allowance from this <hi>Common wealth;</hi> but for the meer Pra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter or <hi>State</hi> enemy, let it be with him as he doth merit. The ruine or impoverishing of many of them is at hand; for <hi>Eclipsis in octava vel septima domo decrescentia &amp; occidentia mani<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>f<gap reason="illegible" resp="#murp" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>stat, fini propinqua, quae jam inclinant ad mutationem, ut sunt se<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nectus, vita functi, consuetudines Leges &amp; institutorum in politiis mutationes. Origanus,</hi> 461: <hi>&amp;c.</hi> An Eclips in the west angle or seven<gap reason="illegible" resp="#murp" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>h house, shews things declining and decreasing; <hi>viz.</hi> such things whereof the Eclips was a significator, and that they are neare unto an end, and that things incline un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>to a Change. Age is here concerned, and so the death of many aged men to follow; Customes and Lawes follow next in order to be altered or some changes to be made in them; Alterations also in things and matters Politicall, as Leagues, Civill institutions, &amp;c. The Eclips having signifi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cation
<pb n="18" facs="tcp:115088:18"/> of things Religious, portends what I have delive<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>red, &amp;c.</p>
               <p>
                  <note place="margin">Who enemies to this Nation.</note>This Eclips ending in the seventh house will manifest unto the <hi>English</hi> Nation somewhat <hi>De apertis inimicis,</hi> what Nati<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on will be their friends, who will openly shew themselves professed enemies. <hi>Libra</hi> hath dominion over much of <hi>Ger<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>many,</hi> and signifies some clandestine Designe in hatching a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gainst our State by some of those petty <hi>German Princes,</hi> as al<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>so so some such like things either in <hi>Flanders, Antwerpe</hi> or thereabouts; Certainly, there is some eminent treason in or near those parts in agitation in or near the time of this Eclips or du<gap reason="illegible" resp="#murp" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>ing its influence to break forth; &amp; if you would know about what or for whom; the <hi>Deflux</hi> of the Moon after her Eclips to the Quadrate of <hi>Jupiter</hi> tels you, its for the re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>stating, or for assisting a King; and who this King can be but the King of <hi>Scots</hi> I know not;<note place="margin">Plots in <hi>Hol<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>land</hi> against <hi>England.</hi>
                  </note> sith his significator, <hi>Jupiter,</hi> who is Lord of the tenth, is cadent in the twelfth, and pere<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>grin, also approaching unto the opposition of <hi>Saturn,</hi> as poor as <hi>Job.</hi> But such is the fate of Princes, against whom the Di<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vine hand of Providence frowns.</p>
               <p>And this my conjecture I also conceive to be sufficiently evinced from the malevolent quadrate of <hi>Saturn</hi> unto <hi>Mars</hi> lately happened; as if either some injury had been lately done unto some of our Nation, or is neer doing, either by some of the <hi>Dutch</hi> or <hi>Scotch</hi> Nation,<note place="margin">Great doubt of the <hi>Engl sh</hi> and <hi>Dutch</hi> a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>greeing.</note> and further intimating no perfect agreement or conclusion with those people, some misfortune or misunderstanding making the breaches either wider really, or else publikely seeming so: Mischief I see is threatned and intended unto us in generall from the <hi>Hol<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lander</hi> and <hi>Scot, quoad capaces,</hi> so far as God shall make them capable or able to mischieve us;<note place="margin">
                     <hi>Hollander</hi> an enemy to <hi>Eng<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>land.</hi>
                  </note> f<gap reason="illegible" resp="#murp" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>r seeing at the very end of the Eclipse the <hi>Moon</hi> her degree in <hi>Libra</hi> doth descend, and the ☉ then first riseth above the <hi>Horizon;</hi> I very much fear a War, or some Warlike attempts either by Sea or Land doe follow: The Lord God of Heaven turn it unto Consultati<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ons onely, and preparations, or Warlike Councels. Let no mans heart fail him; for so far as God doth manifest him<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>self
<pb n="19" facs="tcp:115088:18"/> in this naturall way of judicature, by his creatures the Stars, we <hi>English</hi> have no need to fear the <hi>Dutch:</hi> I wish from my soul a peace with them; but if God have ordained our Nation to be a <hi>scourge</hi> unto the <hi>Dutch,</hi> for their pride and in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>juries offered us this many yeers, I shall rejoyce that the justice of God is executed, but sorely lament either the blood or losse of Substance any Christian shall sustain in this quar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rell. If possible, God divert his judgements from both <hi>Scot</hi> and <hi>Dutch.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>I am not easily inclined to have any evill opinion of that Nation, with whom we have been so familiar, unto whom we have communicated so many helps, both in men and money, as have wholly made them <hi>Libertines,</hi> and weakned our selves; but assuredly the vengeance of Almighty God is ready to be poured forth upon the <hi>Dutch</hi> for their too too much unthankfulnesse. Yet forasmuch as both the <hi>Moon</hi> and <hi>Mercury</hi> are in aery Signs, and in a <hi>trine</hi> aspect, we may well hope that the Merchant as well as others of both N<gap reason="illegible" resp="#murp" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>tions, endeavour a right understanding betwixt us: However, I hope it will not displease the <hi>Presbytery,</hi> if I say our State are promised very fairly to be <hi>Victors</hi> either against the <hi>Dutch, French, Swede</hi> or <hi>Dane,</hi> or any other People of <hi>Germany,</hi> from whom we may have cause to expect an Hostility, or action of War, either by Sea or Land: Y<gap reason="illegible" resp="#murp" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>t assuredly those actions which will be agitated either by Embassadours or Agents, or by Officers of War of any Nation, will be acted with a high and mighty hand, with all the might and power its possible they can prepare.</p>
               <p>We constitute <hi>Venus</hi> Ruler of the place eclipsed,<note place="margin">
                     <hi>Ireland</hi> like to be happy ere long.</note> and she in <hi>Taurus,</hi> applying to a <hi>trine</hi> of <hi>Jupiter:</hi> Were not the mur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ders of our <hi>English</hi> crying unto God for vengeance; th<gap reason="illegible" resp="#murp" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>
                  <hi>I<gap reason="illegible" resp="#murp" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>ish</hi> might begin to be happy; but thrice happy will all those <hi>English</hi> be, who shall adventure their estates and persons into <hi>Ireland,</hi> this Eclipse promising the <hi>English</hi> all happinesse un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>der so wise, so prudent and vigilant a Lord D<gap reason="illegible" resp="#murp" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>puty, and such provident Commissioners.</p>
               <p>But sith this is the first Eclipse, and is Lunar, and so pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>sently
<pb n="20" facs="tcp:115088:19"/> succeding the ingresse of <hi>Sol</hi> into <hi>Aries,</hi> we shall take liberty to intermix part of our judgement with what we shall be enabled to deliver upon the grand Eclipse of the <hi>Sunne.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>The duration of this Lunar Eclipse will be three hours and a half, or somewhat more, and therefore the eff<gap reason="illegible" resp="#murp" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>cts will continue three moneths and about eighteen dayes, be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ginning the latter end of <hi>December</hi> next, and ending in <hi>April</hi> following: But although the effects shall most operate then, yet doubtlesse long before; nay, even presently after its appearance, matters will be making ready and preparing in the fancies and conceits of men. But I forbear further to treat of this, and hasten to the eminent Solar Eclipse.</p>
            </div>
            <div type="account">
               <head>Of the famous <hi>ECLIPS</hi> of the <hi>SUN, 1652. Munday, 29<seg rend="sup">th</seg> March, 9. 56. A. M.</hi>
                  <figure>
                     <figDesc>astrological chart</figDesc>
                     <head>The Sun Eclip<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>sed. ☽ <hi>29: Mar: 1652. 9:56 AM LONDINUM</hi> Angliae:</head>
                  </figure>
                  <pb n="21" facs="tcp:115088:19"/>
                  <figure>
                     <figDesc>stylized depiction of an eclipse</figDesc>
                  </figure>
               </head>
               <p>
                  <hi>NIhil sine Deo &amp; Sole.</hi> Nothing is perfect in this World without God and the Sun; thus said <hi>Clemens Alexan<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>drinus: Omnibus infusus est, omnibus intimus; per hunc ardent in coelo tot syderum faces, per hunc stant elementa, venti spirant, plantae vigent, sentiunt animantes; &amp; quod mireris, eodem temporis mo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mento hic diem, hic noctem inducit; inde serenat, inde coruscat in fulgura, subit in aquas, riget in grandinem, sexcentarum artium unus &amp; semper artifex, caeruleo nubes pingit, <gap reason="illegible" resp="#murp" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>uro vestit montium Culmina, &amp;c.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>
                  <hi>Q<gap reason="illegible" resp="#murp" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>ae in Coelo aut in terris fiunt, hunc orientem omnes natura duce animantes spectant, omnium si quidem proprium est Solis Luce afflatu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>que laetari.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>The Sun is infused in all things, intimate in all things, by him so many glorious Lamps of Heaven do shine, by him the Elements stand, the Winds blow, the Plants florish, living Creatures have sense; and what is wonderfull, at the same moment of time he produces the Day here and the Night there. Here it is faire Weather, by and by Thunder, Stormes and Lightning: He passeth into Waters, then into Hayle; being ever one and the same Artifect of six hundred Arts; he paints the Clouds with Azure colour, cloathes the tops of Mountains with Gold.</p>
               <pb n="22" facs="tcp:115088:20"/>
               <p>Whatever Creatures are either in the Heavens or Earth, all of them doe love the <hi>Sunne</hi> arising, Nature being guide; it is the property of all living Creatures to rejoyce with the Light and refreshment of the <hi>Sunne.</hi>
               </p>
               <q>
                  <l>O Sol qui mediis graderis pulcherrimus Astris,</l>
                  <l>Majestatis apex, &amp; primae mentis imago.</l>
               </q>
               <p>Shall we then say, or be so innocent of the heavenly Or<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dinances, as to deny this great <hi>Luminary</hi> any influence upon humane and mundane affairs;<note place="margin">
                     <hi>Causinus,</hi> lib. 47.</note> or to be so stupid, as to think that when this Light is obscured from us, that there is no<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thing thereby signified unto mortal men? <hi>sint in signa &amp; tem<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pora,</hi> God created the two Lights, or <hi>Sun</hi> and <hi>Moon,</hi> for signs and seasons.</p>
               <p>
                  <hi>Quis dubitat Iridem naturaliter fieri, &amp; tamen huic serenitatis rediturae praesagia Deus annexuit; sic &amp; Eclipsis haud dubie turbato ex defectu Luminarium mundo, morbis, funeribus, casibusque sinistris comitatri solet, quod tam saepe compertum experimentis.</hi> Who doubts that the <hi>Rain bow</hi> is naturall? and yet God hath appointed it the presage or fore-runner of fair weather to be at hand: so an Eclipse, without question, the world being troubled by the defect of the <hi>Luminaries</hi> (viz. <hi>Sun</hi> or <hi>Moon</hi>) is ever at<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tended, as we know by experience, with diseases, sad acci<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dents, as concomicants of it.</p>
               <p>
                  <note place="margin">
                     <hi>Ficinus,</hi> lib. Epist. 6. pag. 120.</note>
                  <hi>Plotinus</hi> the Platonist was wont to say, <hi>eff<gap reason="illegible" resp="#keyers" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>ctus infra Lunam penè omnes à Coelo significari:</hi> all events below the <hi>Moon</hi> were in a manner fully signified or discovered by the Heavens.</p>
               <p>And although <hi>Avicen</hi> was no gr<gap reason="illegible" resp="#keyers" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>at friend to <hi>Astrology,</hi> yet he affirmed, <hi>Coelum est animal obediens Deo,</hi> viz. Heaven is a creature obedient to God. And a little after, <hi>idcirco ouando de Coelestium corporum virtute loquuntur Astrologi, rarissimè quidem aium Coelestia hoc aut illud facere; frequentissimè vero asserunt, tale aliquid aut tale significari:</hi> Wherefore when <hi>Astrologers</hi> doe speak of the vertue a<gap reason="illegible" resp="#keyers" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>d influence of the Stars, or Heavenly bodies, they tarely (I say never) affirm, the Celestiall bodies act or doe such a thing; but very frequently they maintain, they signifie such or such a thing.</p>
               <pb n="23" facs="tcp:115088:20"/>
               <p>And <hi>Ficinus</hi> that excellent learned Priest, in his <hi>lib.</hi> 6. <hi>Epist. fol.</hi> 820. saith, <hi>Multa per Coelum significantur, quae non fiunt in Coelo:</hi> Many accidents are signified or foreseen by the Stars, which are not done in Heaven. And again, <hi>Multa per Coelestia corpora tanquam per signa non per causas praedicuntur:</hi> Many things are foretold by means of the Heavenly bodies, as it were by signs, not by causes.</p>
               <p>The opinion of this man I esteem more then of a thou<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>sand of our own Priests, who bl<gap reason="illegible" resp="#keyers" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>me <hi>Astrology</hi> because it's above their capacity: I pitty their errour, because grounded rather upon malice and ignorance, then a sound enquiry. <hi>Quid de Luminum deliquiis?</hi> (saith <hi>Pucer</hi> pag. 382. <hi>de Astrolo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gia) an horum, Planetarumque his aut assistentium, aut radiis ac<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cumbentium, effectiones inficiabimur, &amp; significata, quorum tristi de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>formique aspectu omni tempore hominum animi conterriti expaverunt, <gap reason="illegible" resp="#keyers" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>repidaruntque, occulto scilicet sensu naturae praesagientes secutura damna?</hi>
               </p>
               <p>What shall I say, or why shall I trifle out my time, saith the learned <hi>Peucer,</hi> against such as deny the influence of the Hea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>venly bodies? What shall we say concerning the Eclipses of the <hi>Sun</hi> and <hi>Moon?</hi> Are we our selves, or any rationall Men ignorant, that the Eclipses of the <hi>Sunne</hi> and <hi>Moone,</hi> and the Radiations and Aspects of the other Planets concomitant and assistant with those Eclipses, their good or bad Aspects each unto other? Doe we not know, saith he, their Signi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fications in all Ages have been ominous, and caused Mens minds to be terrified by a secret and occult sence of the mi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>series and calamityes those Eclipses did presage to be neare at hand or to follow presently after those Eclipses?</p>
               <p>
                  <hi>Neque innoxie unquam vel suam abscondit faciem Sol, Lunae con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tectam interventu; nec opus est veterum annotata ut citemus; usurpe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mus ea exempla, quorum recens in hominum animis viget memoria:</hi> The <hi>Sun</hi> at no time is in vain eclipsed, or hides his face by interposition of the <hi>Moon,</hi> without some prejudice at hand. We need not herein have recourse to what the <hi>Ancients</hi> have delivered, but let us use the examples of our own Age which are fresh in memory.</p>
               <pb n="24" facs="tcp:115088:21"/>
               <p>
                  <hi>Quantos incendit aestus, quam diu flagrantes Solis sub Ariete anno Quadragesimo?</hi>
               </p>
               <p>
                  <hi>Quos motus in orbe terrarum commovit, cum haec Solis, tum alte<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ro anno post Lunae Eclipsis?</hi>
               </p>
               <p>
                  <hi>Quantas lites, quam superba dissidia, &amp; occulta odia insidiasque, quam violenta concilia severint struxerintque, quae bella induxerint, quae pericula nocumentaque frumento fructibusque crearint, deliquia anni quadragesimi quarti; cum Luna tota atra caligine ter faedum in modum deformaretur?</hi>
               </p>
               <p>
                  <hi>Sol plus deunce sui orbis obfuscaretur, adeo ut in quibusdam locis interdiu stellae illuxerint, ac conspectae sint eo ipso et sequentibus an<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nis ex eventu didicimus &amp;c. Peucer.</hi> 382.</p>
               <p>How many hot Summers, how great was the heat, how scortht were the Fields upon an Eclips in <hi>Aries?</hi> What tu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mults and seditions all over the world, did the effects of this Eclips stirre up, when together with one of the Moon the next yeare they were in full force? How great Quarrels, how proud and domineering Insults, Deceipts, Hatreds, what fu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rious Consultations did these sow the seeds of? what horrid Wars did they produce? what harmes unto Corn and unto the Fruits of the Earth did they Create? I mean those Eclipses about the yeare 1544, when as the whole body of the Moon with a fearfull blacknesse was thrice obscured from the sight of mortall man; the sun in those yeares was more then ele<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ven Digits Eclipsed; insomuch that in many places in the day time Stars did shine, and were sensibly apparant. From this and other Eclipses in the following yeares, we have learned by the event of those, what hereafter shall be ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pected.</p>
               <p>But let us come to the intended subject, <hi>viz.</hi> an Eclips of the Sun, and is the greatest this Age hath beheld, from whence you may exp<gap reason="illegible" resp="#keyers" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>ct accidents or effects to follow sutable to the greatnesse; for it was rightly observed by <hi>Ludovicus De Rigij. Prudenter solem considera; nam judicia solis non sunt ob<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>livioni tradenda:</hi> in every greater, meaner or lesser Conjun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ction of the superiors, in every Eclips, in every Radix of any eminent Accident, consider prudently the Sun and his
<pb n="25" facs="tcp:115088:21"/> affection, for in no wise maist thou forget his signification; nor by the leave of the Creator of mankind, will we in our discourse neglect what we may from naturall causes ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tract from this memorable eclips of the Sun in our ensuing <hi>Astrologicall</hi> judgement.</p>
               <p>Divine providence hath ordered this Eclips to be celebra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ted in a fiery Equinocti<gap reason="illegible" resp="#keyers" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>ll signe.<note place="margin">Equinoctiall Signes, what they signifie.</note>
                  <hi>Signa aequinoctialia sunt As<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cendentia regnorum Mundi, per ea quae imperia eorum principia habuerunt, &amp; fundamenta earum urbium civitatesque caeterae quae in principio suarum aedificationum ex istis habente in as<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cendente; omnes imperio proprio conantur dominari regereque.</hi> E<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>quinoctiall signes (<hi>viz. Aries</hi> and <hi>Libra</hi>) are the ascen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dants of <hi>Kingdomes</hi> or <hi>Dominions</hi> of this world, being that or those signs &amp; the <hi>Lords</hi> thereof were strong and well for<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tified when such an <hi>Empire</hi> or <hi>Kingdome</hi> first obtained i'<gap reason="illegible" resp="#keyers" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>s so<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>verainty or greatnesse, or they were the ascendants at what time such or such a City first laid the foundation of its great<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nesse, or when that City had its first foundation or building erected; for every Kingdome &amp; City naturally desires &amp; ende<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vors to be regulated, and to order i'ts or their aff<gap reason="illegible" resp="#keyers" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>ires, accor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ding as the position of Heaven was at i'ts first structure or first arising unto greatnesse: The English nation have <hi>Aries</hi> the Ascendant of <hi>England;</hi>
                  <note place="margin">
                     <hi>Aries</hi> the As<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cendant of <hi>England.</hi>
                  </note> therefore let us observe that as often as either any memorable Eclips doth therein happen, or any eminent Conjunction of the superior Planets, and we shall find cause to wonder at the wise ordering of the Almighty, who thereby acquaints us what he intends to<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>wards us near upon those times, either for our good or e<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vill; and this assuredly and grounded upon the experience of at least twenty generations of men.</p>
               <p>
                  <hi>Conjunctio Luminarium in Ariete facit alterationes &amp; mort<gap reason="illegible" resp="#keyers" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>s: Carda. Seg.</hi> 4. 89. The Conjunction of the two Luminaries in <hi>Aries,</hi> o<gap reason="illegible" resp="#keyers" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>casions strange Alienations of freindship and Death. <hi>viz.</hi> breach of Leagues, Amities and friendships; from thence Warre and controversy, after which follows quarrels, and then Death and Destruction; many times a<gap reason="illegible" resp="#keyers" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>s<gap reason="illegible" resp="#keyers" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap> Famine and scarcity of provisions; for although both the Oppositi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ons
<pb n="26" facs="tcp:115088:22"/> and Quadratures either of the Luminaries or of the Grand Planets are in themselves obnoxious,<note place="margin">A Conjuncti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on most for<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cible.</note> yet <hi>Seg.</hi> 4. <hi>Aphor.</hi> 104. <hi>Conjunctio plurimum validior est oppositione &amp;c.</hi> the Conjunction of the Luminares or Planets for the most is more forcible then either Opposition or Quadrate; from hence let us expect the more manifest and grander effects, where ever Providence shall designe them to fall; for in a conjunction there is union of Beames: Nor are men or Cattle onely concerned in this our great Eclips; without doubt whole Kingdomes, Nations, People, Cities and Common-wealths.</p>
               <p>
                  <hi>Eclipses Luminarium super Civitates, Provincias &amp; Regna, ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gis quam super privatae conditionis homines,</hi>
                  <note place="margin">Many Cities <gap reason="illegible" resp="#keyers" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>nd Common-wealths con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cerned.</note>
                  <hi>aut etiam super Reges; respiciunt enim multitudinem, Seg.</hi> 5. <hi>Apho.</hi> 45.</p>
               <p>The Eclipses of the Luminaries have signification, or o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>perate by their influence upon Cities, Provinces and King<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>domes more forcibly then on Men of private condition or upon Kings; for their effects generally have relation to the Multitudes or Many People. Whereupon <hi>Dasipodius Apho.</hi> 58. did deliver thus much, <hi>Ex Eclipsibus magni effectus proveniunt, viz.</hi> from the influence of Eclipses great and wonderfull effects doe succeed. Nor can we expect lesse from this we now treat of, then great Changes amongst great Kingdoms, Cities, Common-wealths and Families. <hi>Magnorum princi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pum Sol est Significator. Seg.</hi> 4. <hi>Apho.</hi> 107. The Sunne is Signifi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cator of great Princes, Emperors, Men of great Autho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rity. The Moone of Women in generall, and more parti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cularly of Queenes, great Ladies, Empresses, in our present Eclipse,<note place="margin">Great chan<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ges upon E<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>clipses▪ in the fiery Trigon.</note> because it is a Regall house and signe. And sith we have mentioned <hi>Aries</hi> to be a Regall signe, as indeed it is, and the first of the Zodiack; <hi>Leo</hi> the second Regall signe, and <hi>Sagittarius</hi> the third; we shall acquaint Posterity, that the greatest and most materiall Changes-and alterations of this World, have alwayes succeeded either a great Con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>junction of the Superiors, or some wonderfull and great Eclips in the <hi>Fiery Trigon,</hi> whereof these Conjunctions have been the <hi>Prodromi.</hi>
               </p>
               <pb n="27" facs="tcp:115088:22"/>
               <p>
                  <hi>Elementi ignei praedominium ad reges, civitatumque praefectos pertinet; ignis enim agendi efficacia maxime valet; erumpit aestu hor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rendo ignis omnia dissipans atque consumens.</hi> The predominion of the Element of fire, appertaines to the signification of Kings, Governors of Cities:<note place="margin">Eclipses in the Mid-Hea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ven worke vi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>olently.</note> for the vigor and efficacy of fire is very fierce, it violently rusheth forth with an horrible noyse and heat, dissipating, dispersing and consuming every thing which opposeth it. Now for as much as the Sunne, who is by nature hot, becomes Eclipsed in a Signe Regall, hot and dry, and in the most eminent and conspicuous House of Heaven, I say, the effects depending on heat, shall impetu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ously and furiously operate, according to <hi>Cardanus</hi> in the 7. <hi>Seg. Apho.</hi> 76. <hi>Maximus vigor in istis Eclipsibus quae contingent in Coeli corde. viz.</hi> those Eclipses doe most terribly mani<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fest their effects, or doe most vigorously operate, which fall to be in the Heart of Heaven, <hi>viz.</hi> in the Midheaven. With whom concurreth <hi>Proclus</hi> in <hi>lib.</hi> 2. <hi>pag.</hi> 65. <hi>Vehementiores effectus sunt in sublimi &amp; medio Coeli, magnam Sphaerae partem oc<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cupantes.</hi> The effects of Eclipses falling in the Midheaven are more vehement, as occupying a great part of the Sphear.</p>
               <p>
                  <hi>Miros effectus producit Eclipsis magna in signo igneo &amp; regio;</hi> wonderfull are those effects of an Eclips which will follow when it is in a fiery and regall Signe, as this of which we now discourse of is; and as this Eclips hath its first obscu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ration as it were in the tenth house, and its greatest obscu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rity and end neare the very heart or Center of that house, which is <hi>(validior omnibus coeli domibus)</hi> so questionlesse those people who are intended to be made most sensible of this Eclipses influence, are in part <hi>Kings, Emperors, Princes, Dukes, Magistrates</hi> of the highest rank and quality in every N<gap reason="illegible" resp="#keyers" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>tion of <hi>Europe;</hi> and these so great Alterations in this <hi>Macrocosme</hi> shall be so glorious, so conspicuous and apparent, that there is no Nation or people of <hi>Europe, Asia</hi> or <hi>Affrica,</hi> but they shall stand amazed and wonder at the eminency of them; <hi>Solis enim opera manifestissima sunt,</hi> as <hi>Dasipodius</hi> observes, the glorious works of the Sun, or those effects signified by his influence in a great Eclips are the most evident and manifest
<pb n="28" facs="tcp:115088:23"/> and operate the most upon mankind. And assuredly we may expect no lesse then miraculous Accidents to ensue af<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter this Eclips,<note place="margin">Great mat<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ters from this Eclips.</note> it being so great, and the Digits Eclipsed so many; <hi>Maximae eclipses &amp; maximè sperantur;</hi> for the greatest Eclipses produce the greatest effects, and most lively ope<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rate accordingly on that matter they are the forerun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ners of.</p>
               <p>Now forasmuch as this Eclips will be in the Sign of <hi>A<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ries,</hi> and as we said before, that Sign is Aequinoctiall, <hi>Dasi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>podius</hi> Apho. 79. saith, <hi>Signa Aequinoctialia sentiuntur domini<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>um habere super status legum,</hi>
                  <note place="margin">This Eclips <gap reason="illegible" resp="#keyers" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>oncerns Pres<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>
                     <gap reason="illegible" resp="#keyers" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>itery.</note>
                  <hi>ut sunt sacrae ceremoniae, haereses, sa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cerdotia, Pontificatus:</hi> An Eclips in an Aequinoctiall Sign, hath dominion, or shall signifie, or shall operate on such matters as concern the state and condition of Lawes, Cere<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>monies, Heresies, or strange opinions, Priesthoods, Pōpery, or things concerning the Papacy or Prelacy; I may very well adde Presbytery, &amp;c.</p>
               <p>How far the influence of this Eclipse shall operate upon the common Lawes of our Nation, I cannot very well tell; but sure I am, not to its overthrow, but regulating; or how far it shall exasperate mens spirits against the Clergy of our own and other Nations, or how far it shall torment the poor Husband-man, to depart with the tenth part of his labour unto his insufficient or factious Minister, or prating Priest,<note place="margin">The Common Law wil stand but Presbyte<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ry down.</note> I am not able cleerly to determine; great afflictions in one way or other this Eclips doth generally manifest to happen unto all those of the <hi>long Robe, viz</hi> Lawyers, Civi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lians, Clergy-men, and unto those we falsly for the most part call Divines, when God knows many of them have as little knowledge of Divinity, as my self of <hi>Presbyter John,</hi> and as little affection for the Parlament, as my self zeal for Antichrist. But forasmuch as <hi>Jupiter</hi> and <hi>Saturn</hi> were in re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ception, though by opposition, I judge it will goe hard with the Law it self, but not to its extirpation, as some senslesse people would have it; no, it will stand, <hi>viz.</hi> the Law, I mean the common Law of <hi>England,</hi> untill and after that generall Shires are made Provinciall in this Nation;
<pb n="29" facs="tcp:115088:23"/> nay, it will then flourish: but in the interim, much strug<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ling and much heart-burning there will be against it, to no purpose, as to extirpation: for the Law, I mean the <hi>Com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mon Law it selfe</hi> in some more purity,<note place="margin">The Common Law most ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cellent.</note> being to continue so long as men shall inhabit that portion of ground we vul<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>garly call ENGLAND: it is grounded upon pure reason, and of it self is the most equall, and most just Law that ever did appear in any N<gap reason="illegible" resp="#keyers" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>tion, giving every man his right, and tryall by his equals; herein we allow no abuse.</p>
               <p>Nor are the <hi>English</hi> onely concerned in that or those great Catastrophes which will appear after this so famous Eclips; for as it will be visible more or lesse in all or the most place<gap reason="illegible" resp="#keyers" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap> of <hi>Europe;</hi> so according unto <hi>Origanus,</hi>
                  <note place="margin">Institu. Page 454.</note>
                  <hi>Quando Eclipses sunt generales, non modo orbes multas, sed &amp; Regiones in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tegras sub quadrangulo imprimis signi, in quo Eclipsis fit, constitutas; imo &amp; homines habentes cognationem in genesi sua cum themate E<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>clipsis, afficiunt:</hi> When Eclipses are generall (as this almost is) they doe not onely afflict very many Cities, but whole Countries subject to the Quadrangle of that Sign in which the Eclips is: nay, they afflict men also, when the Eclipses have affinity or relation in their Nativity with the T<gap reason="illegible" resp="#murp" extent="3 letters">
                     <desc>•••</desc>
                  </gap>am of the Eclipse: of which hereafter.</p>
               <p>
                  <hi>Nam etsi naturaliter motu, conjunctione vel oppositione nimirum Luminarium prope Nodos sive caudam &amp; caput Draconis fiant: tamen defectus ille Luminis non sine effectu est, cum natura nil faciat frustra; &amp; compertum habeamus, tumultus, seditiones, pestes, fa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mem, grandines, inundationes, calamitatem▪</hi>
                  <note place="margin">Calamities following E<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>clipses.</note>
                  <hi>denique praesertim Sola<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rem portendisse.</hi> S<gap reason="illegible" resp="#keyers" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>tlerus, pag. 74.</p>
               <p>Although naturally by motion in a new or full Moon, neer unto the two Nodes (or more properly to the head and tail of the Dragon) they become eclipsed; yet is not that defect or want of light without effect, sith N<gap reason="illegible" resp="#keyers" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>ture doth no<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thing in vain; and we daily know by expe<gap reason="illegible" resp="#keyers" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>ience, that Tu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mults, Seditions, Plagues, Famine, storms of Hail, Inunda<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tions, Calamities in severall kinds, are ever concomitant, or doe follow an Eclips of the <hi>Sun,</hi> the more great by how much the Eclips is great.</p>
               <pb n="30" facs="tcp:115088:24"/>
               <p>Let us now see in what Asterism or Constellation of the twelve Signs<note place="margin">Of the 12. Signes.</note> this so prodigious an Eclips shall appear; for we are as well to consider the Asterism as the Sign, and the form of that Sign wherein the Eclips is; <hi>significantia Eclipsis decreta sunt ejus, quae proprius cardines; considera etiam naturam stellarum simul consistentium, tum erraticarum, tum fixarum, ac eti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>am simulacra coorientia, &amp; secundum haec pronuntia:</hi> Ptol. <hi>Apho.</hi> 96. Those Eclipses which are apparent,<note place="margin">Constellati<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ons to be ob<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>served.</note> and neer unto the An<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gles of the Figure, doe most apparently manifest their ef<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fects; the neerer unto the Angles, the more vigorously they operate: consider also the nature of the fixed Stars and Pla<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nets neer unto the place eclipsed, and the image and form of that Constellation which arises with the Sign wherein the Eclips is.</p>
               <p>With <hi>Ptolomey</hi> doth agree an unknown Author, in his 254. Aphorism, <hi>Ne obliviscaris imaginum stellarum fixarum, in quibus accident Eclipses vel conjunctiones magnae: quia secundum has accidunt notabiles effectus, viz.</hi> Be not unmindfull of the images of the fixed Stars, wherein the Eclipses or great Conjunctions doe happen; because according unto these, notable effects doe happen: together with these, consider what fixed Stars doe either culminate or arise at time of the Eclips its greatest obscuration. This Eclips then falling out in the 19. of <hi>Aries,</hi> and some few minutes, is in the last part of that Asterism we attribute to <hi>Pisces,</hi> of which <hi>Jupiter</hi> is Lord; and these parts of this Asterism formerly as well as now, <hi>aestuabant, aerem incrassando &amp; obtenebrando, viz.</hi> did heat very much, and also cause a thick and cloudy ayre; and this part being northerly is windy: From whence will arise this judgement, That as <hi>Jupiter</hi> is Lord of the Asterism,<note place="margin">The Asterism.</note> here will be great mutation in the Magi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gistracy of Nations, in the change and alteration of Gover<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nours, in the Lawes, Customes and constitutions of Peo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ple, Cities and Countries, in setling the Ministry in those Countries which are professours of the Protestant faith, much regulation &amp; curbing a seditious, disorderly &amp; ambiti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ous <hi>Clergie;</hi> nor are the Protestants of <hi>Europe</hi> more concerned
<pb n="31" facs="tcp:115088:24"/> then the Popish party; for doubtlesse the Religious orders of houses amongst themselves, will be at great variance and discord amongst themselves, about each others rights, pri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>viledges and precedencies: so also will there be great con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>troversie amongst the <hi>Superiours</hi> of each Order; as also amongst the Cardinals, Bishops, Arch-Bishops, Abbots, and Priors, and such like; amongst and amidst their most serious debates, and in their most private Conclaves.</p>
               <p>There doth arise with the degree ascending a most nota<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ble fixed star of the first magnitude, seated in the right shoulder of <hi>Orion,</hi> of the nature of <hi>Mars</hi> and <hi>Mercury;</hi> and these are in the last part of the Asterism of <hi>Gemini,</hi> whose governour is <hi>Mercury;</hi> from hence will arise dangerous Con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>sultations, clandestine Designs, sudden and violent Coun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cels, pernicious and destructive; this Constellation stirring up the minds and resolutions of men, both Souldiers, Law<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>yers and vulgar men,<note place="margin">Rash Coun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cels.</note> to prosecute their Designs with fury and madnesse rather then discretion; for that part of this Asterism abounding with many fixed stars<note place="margin">Fixed Stars.</note> of the nature of <hi>Saturn, Mars</hi> and <hi>Mercury,</hi> elevates the minds of men, yet subtilly to goe on with their resolutions, untill perfected.</p>
               <p>The northern part of this Asterism in which our Ascend<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ant is <hi>(movet ventos &amp; terras concutit) viz.</hi> stirs up strong winds in the ayre, and strange fantasies in the brains of men; it also shakes the earth, <hi>viz.</hi> the Plants and budding young Trees with storms, hail and tempests; and in man, it ama<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>zes his councels, and puts his wits unto a stand.</p>
               <p>
                  <hi>Eclipsis in signo mobili, rem convertibilem vel ad bonum vel ad malum denuntiat.</hi>
                  <note place="margin">Sea contenti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ons about Fishing.</note> Hermes <hi>Apho.</hi> 80. An Eclips in a movable Sign, shews the matters or things thereby signified to be convertible either to good or evill: And in regard the E<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>clips it self is in the Asterism of the Fishes, it may denote much contention upon Water, or the Seas, about the rights of Fishing, either of our own Nation, the <hi>Hollander,</hi> or some other Northern People: as also in regard <hi>Jupiter</hi> hath significations of Lawes, and Rights and Priviledges Politi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>call, there may be doubted much controversie to arise about
<pb n="32" facs="tcp:115088:25"/> the Priviledges of our Nation, and their rights to the do<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>minion of those Seas our carefull Ancestors have left us; for as the degrees arising in our <hi>Horizon</hi> are almost in a par<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>till quadrate unto the degree eclipsed, and to both the <hi>Lu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>minaries,</hi> being neer unto <hi>Saturn</hi> in an Humain Asterime, hav<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing the shape of two yong Twins or yong Men; it may from hence be probably deduced, that some Men of two severall Nations or Countries,<note place="margin">Caution to the <hi>Engl sh.</hi>
                  </note> or Men pretending one thing to our State, and ayming at another, may joyne in one, or in a League, to bereave the <hi>English</hi> of their Sea-rights, by deceit, fraud, by Treaties, if possible, else in plain termes, by Warre and severall Fleets at Sea.</p>
               <p>For it is excellently well observed by <hi>Rigel Aph.</hi> 55. <hi>Cancer</hi> the sign ascending, <hi>Significator est super aquas multū mobiles, Pisces quoque super immobiles, scilicet lacunas &amp; puteos.</hi> The signe <hi>Cancer</hi> hath signification of such waters as ebb &amp; flow; the sign <hi>Pis<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ces</hi> of such as move not, <hi>viz.</hi> either Ponds, Havens or still wa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ters; it gives us <hi>English</hi> especially warning to beware as well of our decayed Havens, that they be looked unto, as also of our Ships, for feare of surprizals in Harbors; as also to our Navy which floates on the Seas, that either in a calme when not suspected, we be not indangered by fire or other casual<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ties; for we may feare deceipt and treachery in the <hi>Hollan<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>der</hi> and others in stopping up our Harbours or Havens, and must prudently provide also for and against theirs and other Fleets at Sea;<note place="margin">
                     <hi>Hollander</hi> is deceitfull.</note> for <hi>Saturne</hi> in <hi>Cancer, Naufragia permulta<gap reason="illegible" resp="#keyers" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>, Saturne</hi> in <hi>Cancer</hi> signifies many Shipwracks at Sea, many Fleets preparing in severall parts of the World; much thee<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>very and Pyracy, great decay of Shipping, and much inju<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ry to Sea-Townes and their Harbours and Havens; for if we consider the Houses of Heaven whereof he hath Domi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nion, we shall finde him Lord of the ninth in part, and wholly of the eight and seventh; as if in long journeys and Sea Voyages, Stormes, Sea-fights and Shipwracks, many Ships would come to Destruction. <hi>Oportet maximum impedi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mentum esse rerum quae sunt in potestate signi in quo fuerit planeta ca<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>dens aut in malo esse solis.</hi> There will be a great impediment of
<pb n="33" facs="tcp:115088:25"/> such things and in such things, as have relation to the Sign in which a Plamet is posited, either being cadent or in evill aspect of the Sunne.<note place="margin">Sea fights danger to Harbours.</note> Now if the Signe <hi>Cancer</hi> signifie the Sea, as we all know it doth, <hi>Saturn</hi> possessing the Sign, and both in his <hi>detriment</hi> and in <hi>quadrate</hi> of the <hi>Sun;</hi> from hence we may expect such mischiefs at Sea as predicted, and such impediments or blocking up of Harbours, or Sea-fights, &amp;c.</p>
               <p>It addes unto the calamities above specified, that <hi>Saturn</hi> is in a feminine Sign, according to that 83. Aphorism of <hi>Rigel, Majus infartunium Saturni est cum fuerit in Signis faemininis,</hi> viz. <hi>Saturn</hi> is most obnoxious when he is in feminine Signs; but as he is posited now in an Angle, <hi>efficacius producit effectus,</hi> he works more vigorously and to greater purpose: And as we have said, he will operate on the Sea, and in Sea-affairs, so also in regard he is <hi>Planetarum altissimus, &amp; tardissimus ra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ri simè alicui Planetae applicanti, propter hoc significat magnos prin<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cipes &amp; stabiles Monarchas;</hi> being <hi>Saturn</hi> is the highest of the Planets, and in motion most slow,<note place="margin">Great <hi>Turke</hi> is threatned, <hi>Kings</hi> and <hi>Emperors.</hi>
                  </note> seldome applying unto any Planet, unlesse he be Retrograde, therefore he doth sig<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>nifie <hi>great Emperours, great Kings,</hi> such <hi>Monarchs</hi> and <hi>Monar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>chies</hi> as have firmly stood and continued many Ages, or a long time; hereby let the <hi>grand Seignieur</hi> or <hi>great Turk</hi> beware of Tumults and Seditions in his so vast Territories, but especi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ally in <hi>Constantinople,</hi> and in those his Provinces which lye in <hi>Greece:</hi> and so also the Emperour of <hi>Germany,</hi> and many parts of <hi>Austria, Hungaria▪</hi> and <hi>Bulgaria;</hi> nor is the King of <hi>Spain</hi> exempted, whose Dominions and Territories exceed the Emperours: <hi>Aries</hi> being the Ascendant of some parts of <hi>France,</hi> threatens that Nation with War and Bloodshed, with forraign Invasion; <hi>Capricorn</hi> being under the same Quadrangle of the Sign of the Eclips,<note place="margin">Austria, Hun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>garia, Germany <hi>West</hi> Indies.</note> threatens <hi>Brazile</hi> and the <hi>West Indias</hi> all over.</p>
               <p>Nor is there any probable argument to be drawn from hence that the <hi>Dutch</hi> shall recover <hi>Brazile,</hi> &amp;c. it doth ra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther import th<gap reason="illegible" resp="#keyers" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>ir further l<gap reason="illegible" resp="#keyers" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>sses in the <hi>West Indias,</hi> both of Men, Ships and Commodities; nor are they ordained by
<pb n="34" facs="tcp:115088:26"/> Providence to be the Moderators of <hi>Europe,</hi>
                  <note place="margin">The <hi>Holander</hi> must not m<gap reason="illegible" resp="#keyers" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>
                     <g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>derate <hi>Eu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rope.</hi>
                  </note> or its affairs.</p>
               <p>This is the forerunner of more poverty and beggery in <hi>Scotland,</hi> and of Tumults and Seditions in other Countries which lye in more Northerly latitude then 53. and of some preparation of Ships and Shipping, Men, Arms and Am<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>munition, for some Invasion against our Commonwealth: How firmly the <hi>Pole</hi> and <hi>Muskovite</hi>
                  <note place="margin">Pole and Mus<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>covite.</note> are linked in friendship, I know not, they are feverely threatned from the influence of this great <hi>Eclips;</hi> so also is the Queen of <hi>Sweden</hi> threaten<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed to have great division in her Court and Countryes, and some sad misfortune to her Armies or Subjects▪ from such as she very little dreams of.</p>
               <p>Nor can I find the <hi>Danish King</hi> in any security, assuredly some <hi>Navall preparation</hi> he intends,<note place="margin">Denmarke.</note> and much scuffling there will be neer the <hi>Sound,</hi> or in those Seas whereof he claims a Soveraignty.</p>
               <p>And although I find the <hi>Pyrates</hi> of <hi>Algier</hi> will be active in their Pyracies,<note place="margin">Pyrates <hi>Algier.</hi>
                  </note> yet are they signified to have more losse then gain by means of their <hi>Sea-thieving.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>
                  <hi>Zealand</hi> and <hi>Holland</hi>
                  <note place="margin">Zealand, Hol<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>land.</note> may expect further irruption of their Sea-banks, and abundance of losse and damage in their <hi>Ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ritine</hi> affairs, infinite losses by Shipwracks, Storms, Pyra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cies, and without the mercy of God, strange murmuring<gap reason="illegible" resp="#keyers" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>, if no uproar or Tumults of the <hi>Clown</hi> and <hi>Boors</hi> against both their <hi>Provinciall and State Governours;</hi> for if we beleeve <hi>Cardan</hi> in Seg. 7. and 122. Aph. <hi>Detrimenta rerum fiunt maximè locis quae sub sunt ascendenti, &amp; qui in aspectu sunt constitutionum, &amp; his qui eidem sub sunt Trigono:</hi> Those Countries which are subject unto the Sign ascending in an Eclipse, shall suffer exceeding many losses or detriments, as also those who are in aspect or subject unto the same Trigon: Woe unto thee <hi>Holland, Zea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>land, Scotland; Venice, Algier, Constantinople,</hi> &amp;c. if this prove true. Nor is the States of <hi>Venice</hi>
                  <note place="margin">Venice.</note> any way secured, but rather hea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vily threatned with much damage and detriment in their Sea-affairs; much poverty, if not the destruction of some one or more of their greatest Cities, and severall losses unto their <hi>Navy.</hi>
               </p>
               <pb n="35" facs="tcp:115088:26"/>
               <p>The <hi>Genoa</hi> Merchants,<note place="margin">
                     <hi>Amsterdam</hi> past its grea<gap reason="illegible" resp="#keyers" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>
                     <g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>est glory.</note> and the <hi>Amsterlodamians</hi> will assu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>redly smart in their <hi>adventures</hi> to the <hi>East India;</hi> that City hath past its greatest height, and will from hence d<gap reason="illegible" resp="#keyers" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>cline, as having neither sence of Civility or compassion of those who are afflicted. The <hi>Duke</hi> of <hi>Savoy</hi> and his Teritories doe seeme unto me to be aimed at by some petty Princes of <hi>Italy,</hi> or there are a people in Consultation how to beget trouble unto him, <hi>Italy</hi> without doubt hath much to act in this Eclips its effects; wonderfull are the pri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vate Councels of the <hi>Roman Conclave,</hi>
                  <note place="margin">Italy <hi>and</hi> Sa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>voy.</note>
                  <hi>England</hi> is concerned in their Consultations; the subjection of the <hi>English Parla<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment</hi> and <hi>Common-wealth</hi> are the subjects of many private <hi>Councells,</hi> some <hi>Grandees</hi> some <hi>Prince</hi> or forlorn Creatures of<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fer subjection unto that See; Will an <hi>Agnus Dei,</hi> or a <hi>Cruci<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fix,</hi> or a <hi>Popish Relique</hi> though inclosed in a silver Box and Kissed <hi>toties quoties</hi> restore a <hi>Scotish King</hi> to the Crown of <hi>England?</hi> But insurrections, warrs, seditions, one <hi>Prince</hi> in Armes against another may there be expected,<note place="margin">The <hi>Pope</hi> in danger.</note> the Pope be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing <hi>Pontifex maximus,</hi> seems to be eclipsed by some act or other, and in danger either of death, or some private mis<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fortune, &amp;c▪ for <hi>Apho.</hi> 26. of <hi>Ludovicus a Regiis</hi> it is said; <hi>Nec in hoc te esse immemorem volo, quod urbs Romana a Capricor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>no, &amp; Religio Romanorum a Libra principium sumpserint, &amp;c.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>Nor would I have thee to be unmindfull, that the City of <hi>Rome</hi> had its first structure or Renovation from <hi>Capricorn,</hi> and its height to Religion from some eminent Eclips or Conjunction of the superiors in <hi>Libra;</hi> the meaning of which <hi>Aphorisme</hi> is no more then this, that the principall affaires of the City of <hi>Rome</hi> are subject unto the influence of the signe of <hi>Capricorn,</hi> it being under the first Quadrangle and that at what time the high <hi>Priests</hi> or <hi>Popes</hi> did first beget their supremacy over the most Nations of <hi>Europe,</hi> it was up<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on some great Conjunction or Eclips in <hi>Libra.</hi> The onely reason according to naturall causes, why there hath been so many mutations, <hi>Heresies</hi> and severall orders of Religious men and sects in that <hi>Hierarchy,</hi> because that both <hi>Capricorn</hi> and <hi>Libra</hi> are signes moveable: and produce actions as
<pb n="36" facs="tcp:115088:27"/> moveable as the signs; for when as providence had ordered that some eminent Eclips<gap reason="illegible" resp="#keyers" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>s,<note place="margin">When chan<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ges did arise in the <hi>Roman</hi> Chu<gap reason="illegible" resp="#keyers" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>ch.</note> and <hi>great, mean,</hi> and <hi>lesser</hi> Con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>junctions should be c<gap reason="illegible" resp="#keyers" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>lebrated in signes contrary unto the former, then and in those times did many mutations arise in the <hi>Roman</hi> church and all over <hi>Europe</hi> contrary to those the Church of <hi>Rome</hi> had formerly received, generally for the worse <hi>viz.</hi> one error creeping forward in the neck of ano<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther, <hi>Rigel</hi> 32. <hi>Deteriorantur enim genera hominum per transmu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tationes illarum magnarum, cum succedentes inimicabilite<gap reason="illegible" resp="#keyers" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap> configu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rantur cum figuris praeteritarum, &amp;c.</hi> the kinds and qualities of men and mankind are made more degenerate and bad, by transmutation of those great Conjunctions, when as those Conjunctions which succeed are contrary to those went be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore, &amp;c.</p>
               <p>
                  <note place="margin">Family of <hi>Tuthers</hi> how long it conti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nued.</note>And herein we shall need to proceed no further then 1603. the great Cojunction of <hi>Saturn</hi> and <hi>Jupiter</hi> then be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gining in the <hi>fiery Trigon</hi> gave a period to the family of <hi>Tu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tbers</hi> or <hi>Tedders</hi> descended of Brittish Race, which began un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>der the <hi>watery Trigon,</hi> and as it were providentially determi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ned with the Consummation of it, that family having sway<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed the <hi>English Monarchy</hi> about 117 yeares.</p>
               <p>
                  <note place="margin">
                     <hi>Stuarts</hi> family how long it raigned.</note>The family of <hi>Stuarts</hi> entred also upon the govenment of this Nation 1603. somewhat before the Conjunction of <hi>Sa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>turn</hi> and <hi>Jupiter,</hi> which not long after followed, and they continued, I meane two Princes of the <hi>Stuarts</hi> family, about forty years in glory, but in 1642/3. upon the effects of the Conjunction of <hi>Saturn</hi> and <hi>Jupiter</hi> in <hi>Pisces,</hi> a Con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>junction, contrary to their Radix; we know that Families declination; nor is their hopes in Nature of its re-establish<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment or rising again, though there will not want both the industry of men, and assistances of the greatest Princes and States of <hi>Europe</hi> for re-setling that Family; greatest Sticklers in time will appear to be the most unthankfull of men, the <hi>Dutch.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>Nay, this very Eclips doth designe out some such thing, <hi>viz.</hi> severall designs in agitation at present in forrainge parts against the Common wealth of <hi>England</hi> by the Agents
<pb n="37" facs="tcp:115088:27"/> of the <hi>Scottish King,</hi> and I doe fear some secret plots are now acting in forraign parts, yea in <hi>England</hi> and <hi>Scotland,</hi>
                  <note place="margin">Designes in <hi>Germany</hi> to re-establish the <hi>Scottish</hi> King.</note> with intention to make <hi>Ireland</hi> the seat of some further un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lucky War; for <hi>Mars</hi> who doth dispose of this great Eclips in whose house it is; he, I say, is seated in <hi>Taurus</hi> the Ascen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dant of <hi>Ireland,</hi> but in the s<gap reason="illegible" resp="#keyers" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>cond part of the Aste<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>risme of <hi>Aries</hi> which he governs; from whence either war in <hi>Ireland</hi> or great famine is to be expected, with de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>struction of their Cattle, and little expectation of plentifull Harvests &amp;c.</p>
               <p>Seeing we have spoken somewhat of the Asterismes of the signs, it shall not be tedious unto the Reader if I also further expatiate my mind concerning the greatnes of the effects of this Eclips, I do beleeve I shall go very near to hit the mark aright in what I deliver now. <hi>Notabimus imagines Decanorum in quibus accident Eclipses nam secundum illos verificantur effectus: Anonimus</hi> 276. <hi>Apho.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>Let us consider the Images of the Decanats in which the Eclipses are; for according unto them the effects of Eclipses are verified. Every signe hath three Decanates, the first ten degrees of every Sign make the first Decanate, the second ten degr. make the second decanate of that sign, the ten last degr. make the third Decanate. This great Eclips is in the last degree of the second Decanate of <hi>Aries,</hi> and it is the Face of the <hi>Sun;</hi> the first Decanate of <hi>Aries</hi> being governed by <hi>Mars,</hi> this second by the Sun, the third by <hi>Ʋenus.</hi> This second De<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>canate we find to be <hi>Nobilitatis, Altitudinis, Regni, &amp; magni Dominij Imago, viz.</hi> The Image of Nobility, Greatnesse, Do<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>minion, extraordinary Rule: the Ancients did thus repre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>sent the shape and form of it, under this ensuing Image.</p>
               <pb n="38" facs="tcp:115088:28"/>
               <p>
                  <note place="margin">This presents the <hi>English Common<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>wealth</hi> as it will be for 3 years or there<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>about, <hi>viz.</hi> in great Ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>jesty and glo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ry.</note>
                  <figure>
                     <figDesc>man dressed in a long, fur-edged robe</figDesc>
                  </figure>
               </p>
               <p>And though I find and beleeve some <hi>Man</hi> or <hi>Men,</hi> some <hi>Commonwealth</hi> or <hi>State</hi> in <hi>Europe</hi> shall attain unto a very great Dominion or Power, and this by War, Policy, Stra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tagems, Designs, &amp;c. for the twentieth degree of <hi>Aries</hi> where<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>in this Eclips falleth out to be, is represented by <hi>Johannes Angelus,</hi> in the form following.</p>
               <pb n="39" facs="tcp:115088:28"/>
               <p>
                  <figure>
                     <figDesc>man in armor riding a bull and leading a horse</figDesc>
                  </figure>
                  <note place="margin">This presents the State of <hi>England</hi> after a few yeares, <hi>viz.</hi> the sol<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dier tilling the ground, his Armes laid a side, A peaceable time, yet the soldier ever prepared.</note>
               </p>
               <p>His Image, <hi>Homo coopertus capite galea, cum penna strucii Taurum equitans &amp; a sinistris equum ducens.</hi> A Soldier have his head co<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vered with an Helmet, riding a Bull, with the Pen or quill of an he Sparrow, and a spare Horse in his hand.<note place="margin">Some will ac<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>count him so.</note> His Motto or the meaning of his thus riding, is expressed in these words; <hi>Homo malitiosus erit.</hi> This Man will be a malicious Man.</p>
               <p>Yet I say, in regard that this Eclips doth happen in the last Degree of that <hi>Decanate,</hi> and that next <hi>Decanate</hi> is governed by <hi>Venus;</hi> I say, that the Dominion or soveraignty which is signified to be attained by some Man or State at first by deceit and cruelty, or will be attained by War and great labor and industry, fraud, deceit, blood and what not; yet afterwards it shall be ordered with sweetnes; by subtilty, mercy, affability, policy; and this you may observe in the Type following.</p>
               <pb n="40" facs="tcp:115088:29"/>
               <p>
                  <note place="margin">This seemes to promise a cess<gap reason="illegible" resp="#keyers" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>tion of all Taxes and all things go<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>verned by Love.</note>
                  <figure>
                     <figDesc>woman playing the lute</figDesc>
                  </figure>
               </p>
               <p>
                  <hi>Tertia facies Arietis est Veneris, &amp; est subtilitatis in operè, &amp; mansuetudinis: ludorum, gaudiorum &amp; limpidationum.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>The third face or <hi>Decanat</hi> of the sign <hi>Aries</hi> is of <hi>Venus;</hi> and it represents Subtilty, mildenesse, Playes, Joy or rejoycings, Clearnes, &amp;c. A new Soveraignty, or manner of Government, Dominion or Rule is expected to have its first appearance, or signification of greatnesse from the effects of this Eclips; and it shall continue in somwhat a rigid posture; but in much Majesty or austerity, untill almost 1663. at what time all sharpnesse and bitternesse will be laid aside, and matters ru<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>led mildely.</p>
               <pb n="41" facs="tcp:115088:29"/>
               <p>True it is, that upon the effects of that Eclips in 1654. in <hi>Leo,</hi> very great matters in things Politique,<note place="margin">The Eclips in 1654. will se<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cond the acti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ons of these.</note> as Leagues and Friendships may be expected; yet will those Actions rather second and continue what are now and shall be produced upon the eff<gap reason="illegible" resp="#keyers" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>cts of this and these Eclipses on the stage of Mankinde, or first take root and being, then any way checke or countermand them. If we consider the positure of heaven upon the great Mutation of the two superiors in 1603. we shall now finde our Eclips to be the very degree of the then 4<seg rend="sup">th</seg>. House, as if these great Mutations and Cata<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>strophes in every Commonwealth did not by chance or ha<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>z<gap reason="illegible" resp="#keyers" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>rd come to their perfections or greatnesse,<note place="margin">Nature is re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gular.</note> or to their di<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>sturbance and disq<gap reason="illegible" resp="#keyers" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>ietnesse, but by a regular and orderly course of Nature, who acts nothing in vaine, one while exal<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ting and making small Families Great, and againe depres<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>sing other Magnificent Families, even unto Poverty. I say that now the very degree of the then 4<seg rend="sup">th</seg>. House is the degree of this Eclips, and placed in the best and most eminent house of Heaven. <hi>Old things are departed; New Men, new Lawes, new Magistrates, new Commonwealths;</hi> Monarchy generlly disl ked in every Kingdome, every King in Europe either disturbed with the seditions of his owne People,<note place="margin">New Common<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>wealths since 1603.</note> or infested by pow<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>erfull neighbour Princes, every Prince daily in feare of some incursion or other from his Neighbours. This Eclips end<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing in the tenth House. <hi>Perfecta quae jam in Acme sunt &amp; vigent in honore, ut frumenta m<gap reason="illegible" resp="#murp" extent="2 letters">
                        <desc>••</desc>
                     </gap>si<gap reason="illegible" resp="#murp" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>us vicina, aetatem virilem, reges, Magi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>stratus, templa &amp; arces;</hi>
                  <note place="margin">Monarchy disturbed e<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>very where.</note>
                  <hi>viz.</hi> The eff<gap reason="illegible" resp="#keyers" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>cts of this Eclips will have dominion on such things as are even perfect and stand or florish in their height of Majesty, and shine in honour or greatnesse, and are even <hi>as the ripened Fruit or Corne is neere to the Harvest</hi> ready to be gathered and to repose. Th<gap reason="illegible" resp="#keyers" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>se eff<gap reason="illegible" resp="#keyers" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>cts will be manifested on Men who are fully Men, or of middle age, <hi>viz.</hi> from thirty unto fifty; upon Kings, Magistrates;<note place="margin">Quality of Men passive in this Eclips</note> on Churches, Towers, Castles, &amp;c. <hi>Origanus</hi> 462.</p>
               <p>
                  <hi>Res quae a syderibus ex generalibus constitutionibus eveniunt, non sunt unae sed plures, &amp; hae variae atque multiplices. D<gap reason="illegible" resp="#keyers" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>sip<gap reason="illegible" resp="#keyers" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>dius A<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pho.</hi> 20. Those Accidents which doe arise from the influence
<pb n="42" facs="tcp:115088:30"/> of the Planets and Starres from generall constitutions, are not one accident onely, or of one nature and quality, but many,<note place="margin">Various Acti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ons from this Eclips.</note> and those various in their kinds and of manifold nature, or conditions; which is the reason why we doe di<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>l<gap reason="illegible" resp="#keyers" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>te so much on many general things and accidents, and not tye our selves to the old <hi>Mode</hi> of judgements, either of <hi>Jun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ctine, Proclus,</hi> or <hi>Giuffus; Maxime illustres effectus, sunt Solis &amp; Lunae, &amp;c.</hi> very materiall and most famous are those eff cts which are signified by the Sun and Moone, and so we in <hi>England</hi> shall really finde by the effect, proceeding from the Eclips of which we now discourse; <hi>Sol in Anno, Luna in mense,</hi> saith <hi>Escuidus.</hi> The Sun performes his course in a year,<note place="margin">The Sun per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>formes his course in a year.</note> the Moon in Moneths. So also the effects of a Solar Eclips continues for yeers, the Moone's onely Months. Those of the Sunne may continue three or foure yeares, never any longer: that petty <hi>Rabbi</hi> therefore of our own Nation who affirmed the continuance of a Solar Eclips<note place="margin">Continuance of a Solar E<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>clips.</note> might be twelve years, was very far from truth, and more ignorant he shew'd himselfe to be when he would avouch <hi>Ptolomey</hi> to maintaine his Error, whose words are, <hi>Quot horas aequinocti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ales inveniemus, tot annis durabit eventus Eclipsis solaris, &amp;c.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>So many equinoctiall or equall houres as the Eclips con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tinues, so many years the events of a Solar Eclips shall con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tinue. So <hi>Valent. Naibod. Diff.</hi> 4. <hi>p.</hi> 357. <hi>Tempora vero magnorum eventuum non a Saturni &amp; Jovis cōjunctionibus solumodo, sed etiam a deliquiis esse supputanda, vel hinc constare potest, quod illarum eff cta ad longissima tempora protensa, tot ipsorum &amp; aliorum siderum per diversas Coeli regiones transitibus quasi i<gap reason="illegible" resp="#keyers" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>finitis vicibus permutari variarique nec<gap reason="illegible" resp="#keyers" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>ssum sit; Horum autem decreta cum biennium cum semisse nunquam▪ xcedere, queant simpliciora manent, &amp;c.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>The times when great Events sh<gap reason="illegible" resp="#keyers" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>ll happen are not onely signified from the Conjunctions of <hi>Saturn</hi> and <hi>Jupiter,</hi> but supputated also from the Eclipses of the two Lights; or it may be inferred from hence, that the effects of the two su<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>periors have their Portents for a long season, by reason of the so many and infi<gap reason="illegible" resp="#keyers" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>ite transi<gap reason="illegible" resp="#keyers" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>s of themselves and other Planets through the severall Regions of Heaven; therefore
<pb n="43" facs="tcp:115088:30"/> it is necessary that their influenc<gap reason="illegible" resp="#keyers" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap> should severall times vary and change. But the effects of Eclipses doe seldome indure more then two years and a halfe.</p>
               <p>And whereas another pretends himself<gap reason="illegible" resp="#keyers" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap> knowing in <hi>A<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>strologie,</hi> and affirmes, that <hi>Ptolomie</hi> saith, How many houres the Sunne is distant from the Horoscope at the time of his Eclips, so many years it will be ere the eff<gap reason="illegible" resp="#keyers" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>cts b<gap reason="illegible" resp="#keyers" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>gin to ope<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rate; and therefore if the Eclips be in or near the West Angle it may be twelve whole years before the effects take place. Let this Man who thinks himselfe capable of judging <hi>Astro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>logie,</hi> take notice that <hi>Ptolomies</hi> words are these: <hi>Sin autem erit locus d<gap reason="illegible" resp="#keyers" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>fectus in Occidentali angulo, initia erunt tertio quadrime<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>stri, &amp; vehementiores effectiones in tertio triente,</hi> Ptolo. li. 2. cap. 6.</p>
               <p>If the Eclips shall be in the seventh house or West Angle, the beginning of the effect thereby signified shall appeare in the third, fourth Month (that is, after the eighth Month) and untill the twelve Months or nine Months from the time of the Eclips; and the effects shall be more fierce in the third part of the third Month after that time, <hi>viz.</hi> about twenty Months after its beginning.</p>
               <p>The true meaning of <hi>Ptolomey</hi> is thus;<note place="margin">
                     <hi>Ptolomey</hi> ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>plained.</note> Let there be an E<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>clips in the West Angle, the effects thereof shall first shew themselves in the ninth, tenth, eleventh &amp; untill the twelfth Month after its first beginning; and twelve Months after that, or next following the end of the first twelve Months, the eff<gap reason="illegible" resp="#keyers" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>cts shall be apparantly fierce and most operate; but in the last six Months after those foure and twenty Months or two years, the effects shall decrease and vanish; so, that no Eclips of the Sun can extend its influence longer then three years and one halfe from the houre of the Eclips,<note place="margin">No Eclips can extend i<gap reason="illegible" resp="#keyers" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>s ef<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fects ah<gap reason="illegible" resp="#keyers" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>ve th<gap reason="illegible" resp="#keyers" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>ee yeares and a halfe.</note> nor can it be above eight or nine Months before it begin to worke. <hi>Haly Rodoan</hi> was the first that misunderstood <hi>Ptolo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mey,</hi> who, because it was possible that an Eclips which might fall out in the seventh House, might also be distant from the ascendant twelve houres, did unadvisedly say, it might be twelve years ere the effects of some Eclips might begin; him did <hi>Giuffus V. Is.</hi> Doctor of <hi>Naples</hi> follow in that pittifull
<pb n="44" facs="tcp:115088:31"/> peece of his <hi>De Eclipsibus,</hi> and so also some of our litle know<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing <hi>Astrologers,</hi> who take upon them to judge others abili<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ties by their owne weakenesses.</p>
               <p>
                  <note place="margin">Diseases por<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tend<gap reason="illegible" resp="#keyers" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>d from this Eclips.</note>Let our Digression be excused; and let us examine what Diseases this Eclips is the Antecedent of.</p>
               <p>
                  <hi>Conjunctio Luminarium in signis Martis morbos inducit termi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mantes omnino ad mortem, &amp; si fuerit in Ariete ducet infirmos ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tra mentem sine spe, Rigel. Apho.</hi> 84. An Eclips or Conjunction of the Luminaries in the signes belonging unto <hi>Mars,</hi> pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>duces or is the signifier of Diseases tending unto Death; and if this Eclips be in <hi>Aries,</hi> it afflicteth the Sicke, even unto Madnesse without hopes of Recovery, <hi>viz.</hi> with Frenzies, Le<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thargies, Apoplexies, &amp;c. &amp; many other mortall Diseases do most appeare in the Head. Now by reason that this famous Eclips doth appeare in <hi>Aries,</hi> which signifies the Head, such Diseases may be greatly feared; for as <hi>Cor Gemma lib.</hi> 2. <hi>pag.</hi> 56. hath related upon a great Eclips in <hi>Aries; Nunquam tot subito morbis comitialibus apoplecticis sunt extincti.</hi> Never were so many men so suddenly destroyed by the falling Evill and Apoplecticall Diseases as in that year wherein there happe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ned a great Eclips in <hi>Aries. Fluxiones e capite ceu manu com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pressis spongiis defluebant celerrimè suffocantes; augebat vehementi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>am mali constrictus metu sine angustia spiritus, tum sanguis ipse in vasis sensu praesentium, praeteritarum rerum memoriâ ac futurarum horrore concretus, quo nihil ad putredinem vel obstruc<gap reason="illegible" resp="#murp" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>ionem, atque ex consequenti ad febres pestilentes inflamationesque est efficacius.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>Fluxes of rhume distilled or fell from the Head, as if they had been dropt from thence with Sponges, suffocating the afflicted Patient very suddenly. The vehemency of the evill was increased by the silent or mute spirit of feare in the sick without any torment; the Blood also in the vessels, with the sence of things present, and memory of things past and to come s<gap reason="illegible" resp="#keyers" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>emed frozen or congealed, then which there is nothing more efficacious or effectuall to occasion rotten<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nesse and obstruction, and so consequently Pestilentiall Feavers and inflamations.</p>
               <p>
                  <hi>Pestilentiae accidunt afflictâ vi Solis per aerem;</hi> Pestilentiall dis<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>eases<note place="margin">Pestilentiall Diseases.</note>
                  <pb n="45" facs="tcp:115088:31"/> proceed from the ayre when the <hi>Sun</hi> his vigor or in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fluence is restrained or afflicted; so that from the effects of the present Eclips we may fear the diseases before mention<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed to be the companions or attendants of it; and the rather, for that at the time of the <hi>vernall</hi> Ingresse, the two Infor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tunes were angular, and in Cardinall Signs, applying to a quadrature.</p>
               <p>
                  <hi>Notabiliter infortunantur Planetae-per Retr<gap reason="illegible" resp="#keyers" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>gradationem, Com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bustionem, Peregrinationem, Detrimentum &amp; casum,</hi>
                  <note place="margin">When Planets most unfor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tunate.</note> Anonimus 33. Planets are extreamly made unfortunate when they are either Retrograde, Combust, Peregrine in their Detriment or Fall: by how much the more this Aphorism is verified in our present Eclips and <hi>vernall</hi> Ingresse, by so much more the greater evils may be expected.</p>
               <p>In the <hi>vernall</hi> Ingresse <hi>Saturn</hi> was Peregrine, in his Detri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment, and Stationary, towards his Direction; as if he stood still and studied how to punish Man-kind. In the Figure of our Eclips we have <hi>Mars</hi> in his Detriment, and Peregrine; from hence we may expect one mischief in the neck of ano<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther, as also, all manner of <hi>Saturnine</hi> and <hi>Martiall</hi> Diseases, and they generall and very grievous in all or most Provin<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ces and Countries; I mean these Diseases by them signified, will much afflict the poor Commonalty: for <hi>Pessima erit ele<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mentorum &amp; populi constitutio, quando Saturnus &amp; Mars in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fortunati, occupaverint Angulos, cadant vero fortunae:</hi> Its the worst constitution of Heaven, or of the Elements that may be, for the People or Man-kind in generall, when <hi>Saturn</hi> and <hi>Mars</hi> being unfortunate doe occupy the Angles, and the two Fortunes be cadent: In the <hi>vernall</hi> Ingresse <hi>Saturn</hi> and <hi>Mars</hi> occupied the tenth house and seventh, <hi>Venus</hi> was afflicted both by <hi>Saturn</hi> and <hi>Mars, Jupiter</hi> was then Peregrine and ca<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dent in the third: But we are to examine our Figure, and see neer unto what time these accidents or Sicknesses may appear.</p>
               <p>
                  <hi>Cum Almuten Eclipsis vel Conjunctionis magnae pervenerit ad sig<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>na Angularia; &amp; Eclipsis &amp; magnae Conjunctionis accident effec<gap reason="illegible" resp="#keyers" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>us significati,</hi> &amp;c. When the <hi>Almuten</hi> of an Eclips or great
<pb n="46" facs="tcp:115088:32"/> Conjunction shall transit, or by motion passe through those Signs which possessed the four Angles at the time of the great Conjunction or Eclips, then the effects signified either from the Eclips or Conjunction shall manifest themselves. The Signs which were angular in 1642/3 in the conjunction of <hi>Saturn</hi> and <hi>Jupiter</hi> were <hi>Scorpio</hi> and <hi>Taurus,</hi> the last two degrees of <hi>Sagittary</hi> and <hi>Gemini,</hi> all <hi>Capricorn</hi> and <hi>Cancer.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>The Angles of the Scheam in this Eclips are <hi>Pisces, Virgo, Cancer</hi> and <hi>Capricorn; Saturn</hi> for these three yeers last past hath transited <hi>Cancer,</hi> the Sign Angular in the great Con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>junction, and <hi>Jupiter Capricorn;</hi> and from hence hath <hi>Scot<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>land, Holland</hi> and <hi>Amsterdam</hi> suffered, the <hi>Portugall</hi> from the ill disposition of <hi>Jupiter,</hi> as well as the common Law of <hi>England,</hi>
                  <note place="margin">Remarkable Times.</note> and whole Priesthood of our Nation, many of them <hi>very, very, very deservedly.</hi> About the second week in <hi>July</hi> 1652. <hi>Mars</hi> transits the Ascendant of this Eclips, and the second week in <hi>October</hi> 1652. the cusp of the fourth House; the first and second dayes of <hi>January</hi> 1653. he transits the degree culminating at the Conjunction of <hi>Saturn</hi> and <hi>Jupi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter:</hi> In <hi>October</hi> 1653. about the twelfth, thirteenth, four<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>teenth and fifteenth dayss, he transits the fifteenth and six<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>teenth of <hi>Capricorn, viz.</hi> the Angle of the seventh; and the 31. of <hi>December</hi> 1653. and the first, second and third of <hi>Ja<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nuary</hi> 1654. he transits the degrees now culminating, <hi>viz.</hi> the fifteenth of <hi>Pisces: Saturn</hi> in regard of his slow motion, comes not to any of the Angles of the Eclipse, onely in 1653. and latter end of <hi>August,</hi> he transits the nineteenth and twentieth degree of <hi>Leo,</hi> in perfect <hi>trine</hi> to the place eclipsed. Neer upon those times will very materiall and grand Accidents happen, and great distactions in publike Consulta<gap reason="illegible" resp="#keyers" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>ions about <hi>March</hi> 1653. by reason of the Opposi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion of <hi>Saturn</hi> and <hi>Jupiter</hi> in <hi>Leo</hi> and <hi>Aquarius,</hi>
                  <note place="margin">Accidents in 1653.</note> two fixed Signs: After which <hi>(fiunt strages)</hi> as <hi>Cardan,</hi> Seg. 5. Aph. 49. <hi>viz.</hi> after the Opposition of <hi>Saturn</hi> and <hi>Jupiter,</hi> many times succeeds great slaughters,<note place="margin">Two things Principally intended.</note> yea many times cutting to the very ground <hi>great Families, Cities</hi> and <hi>Countries.</hi> And indeed two things seem to me principally to be intended
<pb n="47" facs="tcp:115088:32"/> from this Eclips, according to that of <hi>Cardan,</hi> Seg. 2. Apho. 17. <hi>Considerare oportet tempore Eclipsis vires Planetae dominantis;</hi>
                  <note place="margin">The Generall accidents of this Eclips.</note>
                  <hi>nam non Eclipsis, sed illius significatio apparebit:</hi> Consider the strength of the planet who governs the place Eclipsed; not the Eclips, but what he signifies shall appear, <hi>Mars</hi> governes the degree and signe Eclipsed, but <hi>Ʋenus</hi> is the strongest pla<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>net in the figure: <hi>After famine, the sword and pestilence haue done their parts, I see much good towards Ireland;</hi> from hence I inferr that one thing principally intended is Famin or il Harvests, Dropsicall diseases vulgarly, Tumults &amp; seditions, slaughter at Sea, Sea fights, Shipwracks, the small Pox in abundance, Murrain or sicknesse in great Cattle, after that the Plague,<note place="margin">The Common wealth of <hi>Eng<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>land</hi> exalted from influ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ence of this Eclips.</note> irruption of the Seas or waters in many places. The second thing herein intended doth seem to me to be; The rise or growth of the <hi>Common-wealth</hi> of <hi>England</hi> to a very high esteem all over the world: for Confirmation of this my judge<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment, Let me be heard according unto my owne principles, and not judged without hearing, either by <hi>Tbomas Wiseaker,</hi> or any of the <hi>Priestbytery</hi> according to their unseemly Com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mentary or stupid Annotations on the 10. of <hi>Jeremiah</hi> and verse the 2. <hi>Qui Bavium non odit:</hi> Let him read that puddle of Envy and Nonsence.</p>
               <p>First, it is acknowledged by all except madmen; that <hi>Sol omnibus planetis tribuit vires. Card. Seg.</hi> 5. <hi>Apho.</hi> 171. The Sun gives vertue to all the planets and in <hi>Apho.</hi> 156. <hi>Solis vis est ca<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lefacere &amp; producere:</hi> the influence of the Sun doth heate and produce life▪ and <hi>Being</hi> to every M<gap reason="illegible" resp="#keyers" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>n and Plant and Crea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ture, and as we have said before in this discourse, the works or influence of the S<gap reason="illegible" resp="#keyers" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>n are the most glorious and manifest, &amp;c. From hence is it possible to be inferred we shall give Laws and Bounds to the ambitious <hi>Hollander</hi> &amp; crack-braind <hi>French:</hi>
                  <note place="margin">The <hi>English</hi> to give Lawes to the <hi>Hollan<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>der.</hi>
                  </note>
                  <hi>Aries</hi> we know hath been acknowledged by al <hi>Astrolo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gers</hi> to be the ascendant sign of <hi>England,</hi> &amp; the <hi>English</hi> in their manners subject to the Condition of that Signe, and <hi>Mars</hi> who is Lord of the signe. <hi>Magis autem naturam Arietis &amp; Mar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tis referunt Britania, Germania &amp;c. Ptol: Lib.</hi> 2. <hi>Pag.</hi> 77. <hi>quare in his regionibus magna ex parte homines sunt magis feri &amp; truces. Brit<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tain</hi>
                  <pb n="48" facs="tcp:115088:33"/> and <hi>Germany</hi> do rather follow the nature of <hi>Aries</hi> and <hi>Mars;</hi>
                  <note place="margin">
                     <hi>Aries</hi> &amp; <hi>Mars</hi> for the <hi>Eng<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lish.</hi>
                  </note> therefore in these Regions for the greater part the men are very fierce and valiant. In this signe and in the Degree of his <hi>exaltation</hi> is the Sun at this present, neare unto the <hi>Dragons head;</hi> at the beginning of the Eclips <hi>Aries</hi> arising towards the <hi>Meridian</hi> and in the Conclusion or at the end of it the same signe <hi>Aries</hi> Culminating. Some memorable thing therefore tending unto Honour and greatnesse, or unto glory and Re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nown must of necessity be signified to happen unto the <hi>Com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mon-wealth</hi> of <hi>England,</hi> but a dissipation or subversion of many men now in Authority, <hi>Sol omnium fortunarum maxima est, ne<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>que planeta ullus magis beneficus.</hi> Of all the planets the Sun is the greatest fortune, nor is any planet so beneficiall or bounti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>full unto Mankind; therefore he being in the degree of his <hi>Exaltation</hi> and possessing <hi>Englands Horoscopicall</hi> signe is friend unto our Nation, and will make our Renowne to flourish all over the world. <hi>Faxit Deus. Pugno pro patria.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>The signe wherin this Eclips at present is in, is <hi>Aries viz.</hi> Bestiall;<note place="margin">Rot of Sheepe and Cattle.</note> wherein <hi>Mars</hi> Lord of the Eclipseis placed, in <hi>Tau<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rus,</hi> and are both bestiall; therefore we may feare a Rot of Sheep and some malevolent and pestilentiall sicknesse unto our great Cattle, <hi>viz.</hi> Horse, Cowes, Oxen, &amp;c.</p>
               <q>
                  <l>At, cum sub formis hominum latitabit Apollo;</l>
                  <l>Humanos ventura lues affligere perget:</l>
                  <l>Sub brutis formis, brutorum corpora laedet,</l>
                  <l>Ac segetes, fructusque soli, frumenta, pecusque;</l>
                  <l>Paucis, quidquid erit, signi monstrabit imago.</l>
               </q>
               <p>The Sun so oft as he is Eclipsed in humane signes, which have representation of Men, doth shew sicknesse and other plagues unto men; when he is obscured in brute signs or such as represent Cattle, he threatens the bodyes of Cattle or beasts of all kinds, Corne and Fruits of the earth in every kind &amp;c. <hi>Mizaldus. De eclipsibus.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>This our judgement is approved by <hi>Escuidus,</hi> fol. 21. <hi>Diff.</hi> 1. <hi>Inquiremus quae sunt figurae signorum in quibus erit eclipsis &amp; in
<pb n="49" facs="tcp:115088:33"/> quibus erunt stellae gubernatrices, &amp;c. Si figurae signorum sunt simi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>les figuris animalium, erunt accidentia in quadrupedibus.</hi> Let us inquire what are the formes or figures of the signes where<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>in the Eclipses are,<note place="margin">Foems of the Signs wherin the Eclipses are.</note> and wherein the Dominators or Rulers are; if the formes or signes be alike unto the bestiall Crea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ture, the damages which the Eclips doth portend shall fall upon four footed beasts, &amp;c.</p>
               <p>
                  <hi>Eclipsis Solis cum fuerit in Ariete, significabit interitum Re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gum &amp; divitum, &amp; siccitatem, sive terrae sterilitatem, atque famem. Messahalah Cap.</hi> 7: <hi>de eclipsi solis.</hi> An Eclips of the Sun in <hi>Aries</hi> portends death to Kings, Richmen, drinesse,<note place="margin">Barrennesse, Famine.</note> barrennesse of the Earth, Famine, &amp;c. <hi>Et si fuerit in signo aequinoctij vernalis erit in fructbus arborum, cum oriri coeperint &amp; in aliis quae nascuntur in Ʋere.</hi> If it be in <hi>Aries</hi> in or neare the Equinox, his significa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion will extend to fruits growing on trees when they first shew themselves, &amp;c.</p>
               <p>Whereas I find a generall feare possessing mens spirits,<note place="margin">Caution to the Nation not to fear.</note> concerning the darknesse which the Eclips portends, and some queries whether it threatens not danger unto those people who are either in the Fields about their labouring occasions, or other wayes occupied without dores on their Domesticall affaires; I fay it threatens no Man or Cattle with danger in that consideration; nor will the Darknesse it selfe be of so great or long a continuance as many imagine; about halfe an hour after nine in the morning▪ on Munday on the twenty ninth day of <hi>March</hi> will be the greatest dark<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nesse, if the ayre be serene and cleare,<note place="margin">When the greatest <gap reason="illegible" resp="#keyers" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>ark<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nesse will be.</note> which in some mea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>sure I feare by the arising of <hi>Saturn</hi> neare that time, and the Moon her application unto his Quadratures; however, there is no danger at all to any that shall be the Spectators of it; the darknesse it selfe will not last hardly one quarter of an houre; I mean its greatest obscurity will last little longer; yet I beleeve such and so great it will be for the time that we shall behold the fixed starrs,<note place="margin">Very like to see the fixed Star.</note> as also <hi>Mars</hi> and <hi>Ʋenus</hi> who are at that time South East, <hi>Ʋenus</hi> being more Easterly then <hi>Mars.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>
                  <hi>Solares autem Eclipses nec magnitudinis quidem<gap reason="illegible" resp="#keyers" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap> ratione, eodem
<pb n="50" facs="tcp:115088:34"/> modo vbique apparent: Lumen enin solare quamvis defecerit, cito ta<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>men restituitur. Proclus, in Paraphras. Lib.</hi> 2.: <hi>Ptol. Pag.</hi> 65. Although the Light of the Sun be eclipsed or darkned,<note place="margin">The Sunne quickly reco<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vers his light.</note> yet it quickly recovers it selfe; Now if we will know what manner of man or men he or they must be, who are either already borne and shall occasion so great changes in every Nation, or who they shall be hereafter who shall first manifest their Actions, we must conclude them or those men have either <hi>Aries Leo</hi> or <hi>Sagittarius</hi> the Ascendant or Ascen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dants of their Nativities, or to culminate in their tenth house and to have great relation and Concurrence either with the first Conjunction of <hi>Saturn</hi> and <hi>Jupiter</hi> in 1603. or with their second Conjunction in 1623. &amp; to have either the Sun and Moon in Regall signs or in reception with the superiors,<note place="margin">What signe shall ascend in their Nati<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vities who shall do won<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ders.</note> and they or one of them in Regall signes, or else borne in or neare the houre of some eminent Eclips: <hi>Qui autem nattus fuerit hora Eclipsis, maximè si potentis viri filius fue<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rit, multitudinum hominum causa erit mortis. Seg.</hi> 4. <hi>Aphor.</hi> 97. He who is borne in the houre or time of an Eclips<gap reason="illegible" resp="#keyers" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>, if he be the son of some eminent man of the nation, shall occasion the death of a multitude of men by partaking with him ere he acquire a Kingdome or <hi>Government.</hi> For <hi>Ad regnum adipiscen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dum, ex tribus duo semper necessaria sunt, conjunctio familiae cum successione, bonum aliquod in genitura, &amp; ejus convenientia cum regno.</hi> Two things of three are requisite ever in that man who desires to obtain a Kingdome, <hi>viz.</hi> relation of his fa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mily to the succession, some great matter in his nativity, and the conveniency or concordance of that nativity with the Kingdome.</p>
               <p>For it is very true which <hi>Cardan</hi> delivers in his <hi>Seg.</hi> 7. and <hi>Aphoris.</hi> 166. <hi>Geniturae validae regna mutant; debiles autem ab illis immutantur &amp; fortunam illorum sequuntur, &amp;c. validas autem dico etiam quae malis potentibus subjiciuntur.</hi> Strong Genitures or men who have strong Nativityes do make Changes or over<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>turn Kingdomes and Common wealths; but they who have weake Nativityes or the planets in their Nativityes weake, are overcome or overborne by the former and follow the
<pb n="51" facs="tcp:115088:34"/> fortune of the Victors; I call those also powerfull and well fortified Nativityes in whose Genitures the infortunes bc<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing very strong have most dominion; of this did we make excellent use in our Annual Judgements 1644. 1645. and do very well remember that at what time and as oft as <hi>Ʋenus</hi> did transit the tenth or twelveth degrees of <hi>Taurus,</hi> King <hi>Charles</hi> had ever some memorable successe against the <hi>Parla<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment,</hi> those degrees Culminating in his Nativity; and we all remember that whilst <hi>Saturn</hi> was in <hi>Ari<gap reason="illegible" resp="#keyers" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>s</hi> which was part of 1643. 1644. and 1645. the whole Nation of <hi>Englishmen</hi> groa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ned under a most heavy War; but in or about the lattter end of <hi>May</hi> 1645. when <hi>Saturn</hi> got out of <hi>Aries</hi> into <hi>Taurus,</hi> our happinesse began to appeare by that memorable overthrow of the Kings forces at <hi>Naseby</hi> in <hi>Northamptonshiere</hi> the 14. of <hi>June,</hi> after which we did nothing▪ but Rout and runn after,<note place="margin">Note.</note> and overcome our enemyes. One thing more is observable, that the very 2 of <hi>Sept.</hi> 1644. <hi>Saturn</hi> was in <hi>Aries,</hi> and what is almost miraculous, in the very same degree and but some few minutes excepted, wherein this very memorable Eclips of the Sun now is: <hi>Saturn</hi> was then in 19. deg. 45. of <hi>Aries;</hi> the Sun now in 19 deg. and 15. of <hi>Aries.</hi> There is no earthly things comes to passe without Providence, and an orderly Regulation of Nature by the Command and permission of the great God of Nature; I shall from this strange Antipa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thy onely conclude, That accordingly as in 1644. <hi>Saturn</hi> be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing then in our degree Eclipsed,<note place="margin">Parlament promised well if they pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vent the <hi>Dutch</hi> treachery.</note> did then shew our great<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>est affliction or the greatest Dishonour and Losse this pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>sent <hi>Parlament</hi> have received by the routing and losse of the Earl of <hi>Essex</hi> his Army in <hi>Cornwall:</hi> so I am now as confident the Sun illustrating that degre of <hi>Aries,</hi> that our present <hi>Com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mon wealnh</hi> of <hi>England</hi> shall have such Honour and successe in all their negotiations and undertakings of as great concern<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment for the utility, benefit and happinesse of this Nation, as that sad accident was of sorrow unto them who then sat at the stern, and unto all us little people of meaner quality. Yet there is a Person of the greatest vertue and Honour of our <hi>English</hi> Nation, that can well remember, I told him,
<pb n="52" facs="tcp:115088:35"/> after the 10. or 12. of <hi>June</hi> 1645; the King would no more thrive, &amp;c. What are the true Genitures of either the valiant Lord <hi>Fairfax</hi> or any other since of all our Generall Offi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cers, I doe not perfectly know, yet some I doe, and these have Nativityes exactly contradictory to the late <hi>Kings:</hi> it's enough that the degree of the last Conjunction of <hi>Saturn</hi> and <hi>Jupiter</hi> is in the cuspe of the seventh house in the Nati<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vity of one expecting to be a great man, but must not; some may be so Criticall as to demand when shall these things by us spoken come to passe,<note place="margin">When the ac<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cidents shall come to passe.</note> or whether all on a suddaine, and in every Region at or neare the same time? unto that I answer: <hi>Climatum differentia facit ut celerius aut tardius eventus proveniant.</hi> The difference of Climates occasions that the effects of Eclipses do sooner come to effect in one Country, and later in another; for neither doth the Sun rise in every Kingdome at one houre. Somewhat will be expected we should say, concerning those on whose Nativityes any of these Eclipses may have concernment, and they are onely those, who have either the Sun or Moon in the 6. degree of <hi>Aries</hi> or <hi>Libra</hi> or 6. degr. of <hi>Cancer</hi> or <hi>Capricorn,</hi> according to the first Eclips of the Moon in <hi>March.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>
                  <note place="margin">Who concer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ned in the E<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>clipses.</note>They are concerned in the influence of the great Eclips of the <hi>Sun,</hi> who have either the nineteenth or twentieth of <hi>Aries,</hi> or of <hi>Libra,</hi> or of <hi>Cancer</hi> or <hi>Capricorn,</hi> the place of their <hi>Sun</hi> or <hi>Moon</hi> at the time of their Births.</p>
               <p>They are concerned in the operation of the second Eclips of the <hi>Moon,</hi> who have either the <hi>Sun</hi> or <hi>Moon</hi> Ascendant or Mid heaven in the 25. degr. of <hi>Pisces, Virgo, Sagittarius</hi> or <hi>Gemini;</hi> wherein the King of <hi>Scotland</hi> may claim the greatest share in the effects of the last Lunar Eclips, &amp;c.</p>
               <p>The King of <hi>Spain</hi>
                  <note place="margin">King of <hi>Spain.</hi>
                  </note> hath the <hi>Sun</hi> in his Nativity in 19. d. of <hi>Aries</hi> (if I am rightly informed) and the Dragons tail there also; happy may he be, if he, I say he himself, escape either blindnesse, or some hurt to one of his Eyes, or some sad fate (if not death) ere the influence of this Eclips de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>termine, let him beware of fire, powder, treason, or hot Feavers: he is like to be much concerned either in himself
<pb n="53" facs="tcp:115088:35"/> or Children (if he have any) from this dire influence, &amp;c.</p>
               <p>Many I know wlll be apt to misapply our words, and to conceive we intend the influence of this Eclips to fall gene<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rally over or upon every Nation of <hi>Europe;</hi> these men seem to know nothing; for <hi>nulla Eclipsis omnino toti orbi penuriam au<gap reason="illegible" resp="#keyers" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap> pestem pronunciare potest; pestis autem ex his, nunquam quatuor annis durare potest,</hi> Cardanus,<note place="margin">When we may expecta terri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ble Plague.</note>
                  <hi>Seg.</hi> 7. <hi>Apho.</hi> 121. No Eclips can signifie penury or scarcity, or a Pestilence to be generall unto the whole World; for a Pestilence or Plague derived from the influence of an Eclips either Solar or Lunar, can<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>not last above four yeers, &amp;c. but we have no such generall Calamity now threatned upon <hi>England;</hi> let such a thing be expected from the effects of the Eclips in 1654. at what time <hi>Saturn</hi> is got into the fiery Sign <hi>Leo,</hi> and not far removed from the <hi>Luminaries</hi> in the Eclips.</p>
               <p>For although it be most true, that the Planet who dispo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>seth of the place of the Eclips, shall mostly shew what man<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ner or quality the effects shall be of, yet are they more or lesse, great or little, more forcible, or more restrained, ac<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cording to the quality of that Planets existence and forti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tude at time of the Eclips. <hi>Mars</hi> disposeth the Eclips; what he signifieth, see in our method of Eclipses following, &amp;c.</p>
               <p>
                  <hi>Stellae quae disponunt Eclipsium loca, si noviter emergunt aut occul<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tantur, aut stationem ingrediuntur, vel noctu emicant, augent vel minuunt effectus: Augent quidem dum é Solis radiis emergunt &amp; in stationibus sunt; etsi enim debiliores sint, quia tamen firmi manent in uno loco plus operantur; debilis enim assiduè assistens plus operatur, quam validus vagans: Minuunt vero effectus cum occultantur Plane<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tae dispositores &amp; noctu emicantes &amp; retrogradi.</hi> Dasipodius <hi>A<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pho.</hi> 76.</p>
               <p>Those Stars or Planets which dispose of the places or de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>grees of the Eclips, if they doe either newly separate from the <hi>Sun</hi> beams, or appear before them, or are obscur'd or clouded by them, or they enter their station, or shine in the night, doe either encrease or dimi<gap reason="illegible" resp="#keyers" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>ish the effects: they veri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly doe encrease the effects of the influence whilest they are hastening from the <hi>Sun</hi> beams, and are in their stations; for not
<pb n="54" facs="tcp:115088:36"/> although they then appear to be more weak, yet because they remain firm in one place (this is understood by a stationary Planet) they more effectually send down their influence; for a weak Planet being ever at work, doth more strongly ope<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rate then a stronger Planet, who is w<gap reason="illegible" resp="#keyers" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>ndring in motion, and not at all fixed; for Planets who are Dispositors of Eclip<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ses,<note place="margin">Planets weak when under the earth.</note> when they are obscured by the <hi>Sun</hi> beams, are of lesse ef<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fect, as also when they are Retrograde, and shine in the night, <hi>viz.</hi> are seen after the <hi>Sun</hi> set; for you must know, the vertues of all Planets are extreamly weakned when their bodies are subterranean.</p>
               <p>We shall draw unto a conclusion, affirming that about <hi>June,</hi>
                  <note place="margin">Effects begin aboet <hi>August</hi> 1652.</note>
                  <hi>July, August</hi> and <hi>September</hi> next, there will be an ap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pearance of some memorable actions, which in part will de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>clare a beginning of many others to succeed in the like kind, probably Eastward, towards <hi>March, April</hi> and <hi>May</hi> 1653. and so following; or neer those three Moneths, the Eclips its effects will begin to be in their fullest vigour and glory, but much in Consultations or Treaties; and towards <hi>Sep<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tember, October</hi> and <hi>Novemb.</hi> 1653. a little begin to lessen: Cer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tainly it is the fore-runner of the eclipsing or diminishing of the Glory, Majesty and Dominion of many men now in present Authority, both in <hi>England</hi> our own Nation, and also the <hi>Netherlands, Spain</hi> and <hi>France,</hi> which miserable and divided Country I pitty; yet <hi>France</hi> must be invaded, and the King thereof become most unfortunate.</p>
               <p>The time of the events signified by this Eclips, ending a little after that time which this present Parlament seems to have voted to give a period to their sitting; it is therefore very probably to be gathered from the effects of this Eclips, that in good earnest the Souldier and People will joyn in one for calling a <hi>New Representative</hi>
                  <note place="margin">New Repre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>sentative.</note>
                  <hi>in this Commonwealth:</hi> for the <hi>Moon,</hi> who signifieth the People, eclipseth the <hi>Sun;</hi> as if nothing would satisfie our earnest desires but that which perhaps it had been better for us to decline, it being more easie to repair an old house, then build a new.</p>
               <q>Sic transit gloria Mundi.</q>
               <pb n="55" facs="tcp:115088:36"/>
               <p>Now forasmuch as the <hi>Sun</hi> hath representation of the Commonwealths Treasurer and Treasury, being Lord of the second house, this Eclips doth admonish all such as have had fingering in the Treasure of the Commonwealth, to prepare their Accompts; for their day of judgement is com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing; and very great reason it should, for if <hi>Vox Populi</hi> be <hi>Vox Dei,</hi> it is generally conceived there is privately detained in severall Treasurers hands,<note place="margin">Treasurers must accompt</note> and in such as have been Colle<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ctors for this State, more mony then would pay the Army one yeers wages.</p>
               <p>Our State endeavour by their prudent Commissioners in <hi>Scotland</hi> to settle that Nation; I doe perceive by this Eclips whatever the best of the <hi>Scots</hi> promise, falshood is intended,<note place="margin">
                     <hi>Scots</hi> very fals</note> and private Conspiracies will be managed betwixt many of the People and Priests, for outing us in those parts, they having no eyes to see their happinesse by Union with us; how great a misfortune therefore it is, any People may fee by this onely act of theirs, to see with no other eyes but those of the Clergy, many whereof are tenebrous, and very few clear without spots, <hi>viz.</hi> in their understandings and crazy Noddles: The influence of this Eclips will deprave mens tempers, or the constitutions of mens Bodies,<note place="margin">Ayre corrupt<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed.</note> so far as they have connexion with the Elements, by reason the Ayre in many places will be infected with grosse vapours, and un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>wholsome sudden blasts of Wind, tempestuous and unprofi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>table. The Autumns of these two yeers I much fear will be unhealthy, &amp; People apt to surfet or create Maladies in their Stomacks, &amp;c. from those infections; Agues, Dropsies, Tym<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>panies, more then vulgar will appear; but who it is shall suffer this fate following, I leave to times discovery:
<q>
                     <l>Sublatus fortè veneno,<note place="margin">Sudden death to some great man, by stab<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bing, or the like.</note>
                     </l>
                     <l>Aut caesus gladio, subita vel morte vocatus.</l>
                  </q>
               </p>
               <p>We will conclude this Treatise with our own <hi>Astrologicall Judgement</hi> of this yeer 1652. delivered by us, and printed 1644. in our <hi>Propheticall Merlin,</hi> pag. 115.</p>
               <pb n="56" facs="tcp:115088:37"/>
               <p> Strange Apparitions, and unusuall sights in the Southeast parts.</p>
               <p>A yeer full of Embassages.</p>
               <p>A preparative in the Heavens for a great Plague.</p>
               <p>
                  <hi>Florentines</hi> make Tumults.</p>
               <p>
                  <hi>Italy</hi> is fearfull. Wars in <hi>Bohemia.</hi> Ʋproars in <hi>Rome.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>
                  <hi>Scotland</hi> beware a Famine. <hi>ENGLAND</hi> be thou Content.</p>
               <p>Also in page 110. we say;</p>
               <p>Wo to a great <hi>Family</hi> of <hi>EVROPE,</hi> that was, is now, but shall be no more, &amp;c.</p>
               <q>Qui potest capere, capiat.</q>
               <p>We conclude with these Verses of <hi>Chrysippus:</hi>
                  <q>
                     <l>Quam falsò accusant superos, stultique queruntur</l>
                     <l>Mortales! etenim nostrorum causa malorum</l>
                     <l>Ipsi nos sumus &amp; sua quemque vecordia laedit.</l>
                  </q>
               </p>
            </div>
            <div type="account">
               <pb n="57" facs="tcp:115088:37"/>
               <head>The <hi>MOON</hi> Eclipsed, <hi>September 7<seg rend="sup">th</seg>. 1653.</hi>
                  <figure>
                     <figDesc>astrological chart</figDesc>
                  </figure>
               </head>
               <p>NOthing is more memorable in this Lunar Eclips then that the degree eclipsed was the true place of the last Conjunction of <hi>Saturn</hi> and <hi>Jupiter</hi> 1642/3. and as that Con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>junction was celebrated in the second house, intimat ng the infinite trouble that some men should have to preserve <gap reason="illegible" resp="#keyers" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>heir Estates, who were of such Families, or descended <gap reason="illegible" resp="#murp" extent="3 letters">
                     <desc>•••</desc>
                  </gap>m such as had any relation to <hi>Saturn</hi> at the time of their Fam lies
<pb n="58" facs="tcp:115088:38"/> first erection; so also it did declare the sudden &amp; unexpected preferment of some other Families, who had their originall preferment, or first greatnesse under either <hi>Sagittarius</hi> or <hi>Pisces:</hi> Now this Lunar Eclips beginning in the Ascendant, and passing through the twelfth house, the Dispositor of the Eclips being <hi>Jupiter,</hi> weak and in his Fall, it imports the great difficulties severall of those then, and since, eminent Men, shall goe thorough to preserve that Estate and Honour they have since 1642. acquired; not without much affliction of mind shall they now preserve that Honour or esteem they have so long enjoyed; a secret hand of P<gap reason="illegible" resp="#keyers" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>licy, or a repining People, either by cunning or violence, dispossessing them of part of their Estates, and all or most of their Honour: <hi>jam seges est.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>This Eclips seems to me to be the Messenger or Antece<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dent of corrupt ayre, unwholsome W<gap reason="illegible" resp="#keyers" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>ather, infecting the generality of People with abundance of corrupt Humours, thereby preparing matter for those pestilentiall Diseases ap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>proaching.</p>
               <p>This Eclips beginning in the Ascendant, begins very soon to operate, <hi>viz.</hi> according to our method and <hi>Ptolomey's,</hi> within three moneths after its beginning, and ends about the middle of <hi>December</hi> following: its the Significator of Sea fights, or dammage to Ships, Sailors, Fisher-men; of some peremptory requests in the Presbyt<gap reason="illegible" resp="#keyers" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>ry, or some secret Consultations of theirs, for their advancement or re-esta<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>blishment; of the imprisonment of some dis-affected people to our Commonwealth, of distraction in or about the Law, or Courts of Justice; much unwillingnesse of the Com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>monalty to contribute to their Ministers: some treasonable designs in action or Councell against the Magistracy; hopes and desires in the Ministers to subject the Parlament to their Lawes.</p>
               <p>Many disasters in the <hi>West Indies,</hi> great losse unto the <hi>Por<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tingall;</hi> famine and scarcity approaching in <hi>Italy;</hi> sad news from the <hi>East Indies;</hi> sudden Commotions in <hi>Paris,</hi> or in many parts of <hi>France;</hi> a very troublesome and unquiet Au<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tumn;
<pb n="59" facs="tcp:115088:38"/> many State officers in question <hi>ubicunque;</hi> many in Authority in great fear and tribulation; abundance of Sick<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nesses, as Agues, Tumors and Gouts, small Pocks, Lethargies, Palpitation of the Heart, black Jaundies, Cholick, torment in the Guts, many Women miscarrying through fear and frights; a sad time with the <hi>Dutch</hi> in many places of the World; no good time for the King or Governours of <hi>Spain</hi> and his Territories.</p>
               <p>
                  <hi>Signa Communia in homines, Reges Magistratus,</hi> Dasipod. 69. When Eclipses are in common Signs, the influence hath most effect on men, Kings, Magistrates. The Eclips is in par<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>till opposition unto the degree ascending of the King of <hi>Scots; Pernitiosior est ea Eclipsis quae accidet in Horoscopo, genitura<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rumque quae in ortivo annuarum conversionum Cardine; portenditur enim nato illi malum aliquod exitiosum in corpore ejus vitalique sub<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>stantia:</hi> Thus saith <hi>Junctine, in Tractatu de Eclip.</hi> pag. 307.</p>
               <p>That Eclips is more dangerous or pernitious which shall be in the Horoscope or <hi>Ascendant</hi> of the birth; or which shall be in the degree Ascending in an Annuall <hi>Revolution:</hi> it portends unto the Native some ominous and mischievous action as unto his body and also in his vitall substance; Perhaps he shall be deprived of his <hi>French Pension.</hi> We shall Conclude with one observation more of the said <hi>Junctine</hi> who further saith;</p>
               <p>
                  <hi>Loca eclipsium aut opposita, nodusque Meridianus si acciderint in Horoscopo natalitij thematis, aut locis luminarium, praecipuè conditi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>onarij, natus ille cujus fuerit genitura, in maximis vitae versabitur pe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>riculis, quae magna cum difficultate evitari poterunt: imo è vita disce<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>det, si anni illius Rex, &amp; Horoscopi dominus &amp; divisor in utroque themate, natalis scilicet &amp; revolutionis fuerint malè affecti, &amp;c.</hi> 307.</p>
               <p>Either the Degrees Eclipsed or their opposits, and the South N<gap reason="illegible" resp="#keyers" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>de, if these happen in the Ascendant of the Radix of any one in his nativity, or especially the Luminarie of the time, he whose Nativity that shall be, shall be plunged with many misfortunes and casualtyes in his life, which cannot be avoyded with<gap reason="illegible" resp="#keyers" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>ut great difficulty: nay, if the Lord of the Ascendant of that yeare when the Eclips is, and
<pb n="60" facs="tcp:115088:39"/> the Divisor of the profectionall figure and the Lord of the radicall figure be ill-affected, then it may be much feared he will be in danger of Death: The continuance of this Eclips is about 3 hours and 20. minut<gap reason="illegible" resp="#keyers" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>s: and therfore the Events shall expresse themselves three whole moneths and lesse then a halfe moneth, or about three moneths and twen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ty dayes, &amp;c.</p>
               <p>If any desire to veiw those Quadrangles of the signes un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>to which the Kingdomes, Nations, Cities or Countries of <hi>Europe</hi> which are like to be passive in the effects of this Eclips, are subject unto; Let them peruse Master <hi>Bookers Al<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>manack</hi> of 1652.</p>
            </div>
            <div type="aphorisms">
               <head>Astrologicall Aphorismes.</head>
               <p>HE who is naturally well affected unto Astrology shall verily pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nounce more certain Judgements.</p>
               <p n="2">
                  <hi>2</hi> Divers effects of the Starrs are drawnforth of the Starrs, ac<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cording to the various dispositions of the matter: whereof the Astrolo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ger ought very well to examine the severall natures and qualityes of the Subjects receiving.</p>
               <p n="3">
                  <hi>3</hi> Because alwayes matter determines the form, it comes to passe that we doe freely by our wicked operations conceive our Starrs to pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>duce those Detriments unto us.</p>
               <p n="4">
                  <hi>4</hi> The formes wherewith the Heavenly bodies do operate, are cal<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>led Images, unto which the formes inferiour are subject: these are ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ny in the signes, Decanates, and Degrees, in some Stars, they are se<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>perate and in many joyn'd together.</p>
               <p n="5">
                  <hi>5</hi> The visible or sensible Images of the <hi>8<seg rend="sup">th</seg>
                  </hi> Sphear are very ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ny, and many are made dayly there by the Planets: all which ought to be considered of the Astrologer: they have all great efficacy upon infe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rior bodies.</p>
               <p n="6">
                  <hi>6</hi> A Figure is not active (as some Platonists say) but the form, wherein the substance operates.</p>
               <p n="7">
                  <pb n="61" facs="tcp:115088:39"/>
                  <hi>7</hi> When he who consults produceth the Sigillation of his Constel<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lation moving him thereunto, how sufficiently then may<gap reason="illegible" resp="#keyers" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>st thou then re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>solve that matter propounded.</p>
               <p n="8">
                  <hi>8</hi> The signes have their Heterogeniall parts of the Element and answering to the Heaven, which we call the Termes of the <hi>5</hi> Planets.</p>
               <p n="9">
                  <hi>9</hi> Because Images, and inferior mutations, are subject to inferiors, therefore we must prudently by similitude and Analogy search out the Actions and significations of the Heavenly bodies.</p>
               <p n="10">
                  <hi>10</hi> The parts of our body are Heterogeniall, and therefore accor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ding to their proper temperaments are subject to divers Planets.</p>
               <p n="11">
                  <hi>11</hi> The significations of things are threefold, na<gap reason="illegible" resp="#keyers" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>urall, acciden<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tall and speciall; the speciall are first to be inquired, next the acci<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dentall, after that, the Naturall.</p>
               <p n="12">
                  <hi>12 Sol</hi> and <hi>Mars</hi> are fiery; the heat of <hi>Mars</hi> is d<gap reason="illegible" resp="#keyers" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>structive, that of the Sun answers the vivifying heavenly fire.</p>
               <p n="13">
                  <hi>13 Mercury</hi> is hot, cold, dry and moist in the frrst degree, as some will have it; but he hath an indifferent and Convertible nature.</p>
               <p n="14">
                  <hi>14 Venus</hi> is cold in the second degree, moyst in the third; the Moon is cold in the third degree, moyst in the fourth <hi>Jupiter</hi> is hot in the second degree, moyst in the first; the Sun is hot in the third degree dry in the second. <hi>Mars</hi> is dry in the third, hot in the fourth. <hi>Saturn</hi> is cold and dry in the fourth degree.</p>
               <p n="15">
                  <hi>15</hi> The superior Planets are most essicacious; the inferior are weake, and easily do suffer by the superiors, and receive either good or ill from them.</p>
               <p n="16">
                  <hi>16</hi> Superior Planets because they much resist, they doe not easily receive a detriment, or good turn from the inferior Planets.</p>
               <p n="17">
                  <hi>17</hi> The misfortunes proceeding from <hi>Saturn</hi> and <hi>Mars</hi> are mi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tigated if their places are protected by <hi>Jupiter,</hi> being well disposed and in good aspect.</p>
               <p n="18">
                  <hi>18</hi> When a Planet who is a fortune, is in Conjunction with an in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fortune, he allayes his malice, so that the infortune shall do no hurt.</p>
               <p n="19">
                  <hi>19</hi> The fixed Stars are the most efficacious of all in their opera<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tions; for what actions they manifest or occasion are very great.</p>
               <p n="20">
                  <hi>20</hi> The fixed Stars doe imitate the nature and action of the Er<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>raticals or Planets; wherefore they transfer their actions unto them.</p>
               <p n="21">
                  <pb n="62" facs="tcp:115088:40"/>
                  <hi>21</hi> The Moon hath a certaine naturall mutability, therefore she easily communicates unto us the influence of other Stars.</p>
               <p n="22">
                  <hi>22</hi> The Moon doth then most especially transfer Actions unto the inferior World, and the influx of other Stars from whom she is sepera<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ted, when she is swift in motion.</p>
               <p n="23">
                  <hi>23</hi> Three manner of wayes the Planets are varied or changed, by reason of their first qualities of their houses and significations.</p>
               <p n="24">
                  <hi>24 Saturn</hi> governs Contemplation and Memory: <hi>Mars</hi> Boldnes and fortitude, if they want not strength, or are ill disposed.</p>
               <p n="25">
                  <hi>25</hi> Retrograde Planets degenerate from their proper nature, by that meanes Fortunes are made infortunes, and the evill Planets farre worse.</p>
               <p n="26">
                  <hi>26</hi> Planets do manifest greater and worser evils when they are Stationary, then when Retrograde.</p>
               <p n="27">
                  <hi>27</hi> The Reception of Planets when they behold one another, if it be strong, doth diminish the malice of an evill aspect, and increases the goodnesse of a good aspect.</p>
               <p n="28">
                  <hi>28</hi> A Planet in an Angle doth more effectually produce his effects, but remisse in cadent houses.</p>
               <p n="29">
                  <hi>29</hi> Be not too confident either of a sextill or trine aspect in violent Signes, nor out of those Signes in which the Planets behold one ano<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther, yet essentially suffer.</p>
               <p n="30">
                  <hi>30</hi> Consider what things the Planets perform not by their aspects, and observe if they doe them not by their Antiscions; for the Antisci<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ons have power, and are to be enumerated amongst aspects.</p>
               <p n="31">
                  <hi>31</hi> Its rare if any Planet prove a fortune in the eight or twelfth, by reason of the malignancy of those houses.</p>
               <p n="32">
                  <hi>32</hi> The qualities of <hi>Saturn</hi> and <hi>Mars</hi> are not made better by their conjunction: being mixed so together they are confounded, and hurt very much.</p>
               <p n="33">
                  <hi>33</hi> Planets are notably made unfortunate by these Accidents, <hi>viz.</hi> Combustion, Retrogradation, Peregrination, Detriment and fall.</p>
               <p n="34">
                  <hi>34</hi> The swift and various motions of the Planets are to be consi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dered, as also their slownesse; because when they vary, the accidents of the aspects doe alter.</p>
               <p n="35">
                  <hi>35 Saturn</hi> seldome applies to any Planet, by reason whereof he signifies great Princes and firme Monarchs.</p>
               <p n="36">
                  <pb n="63" facs="tcp:115088:40"/>
                  <hi>36</hi> A partill Aspect comes to passe within the difference of three degrees, a platicke Aspect happens by a semediameter of the Orbs of the Planets.</p>
               <p n="37">
                  <hi>37</hi> The vertue of a Planet is in that House, whose beginning or Cuspe a Planet precedes by no greater space then five degrees.</p>
               <p n="31">
                  <hi>31</hi> Vnderstand the simple qualityes of the Planets for from thence thou shalt know all their mixt significations.</p>
               <p n="39">
                  <hi>39</hi> Those houses which behold not the Ascendant, signifie occult or obscu<gap reason="illegible" resp="#keyers" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>e places, and these houses are the <hi>12: 8.</hi> and <hi>6.</hi>
               </p>
               <p n="40">
                  <hi>40</hi> The application of Planets shews what is to come, the sepera<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion what is past.</p>
            </div>
            <trailer>FINIS.</trailer>
         </div>
      </body>
      <back>
         <div type="publishers_advertisement">
            <opener>
               <salute>READER,</salute>
            </opener>
            <p>FOr the great satisfaction I have my self received thereby, and the excellent Divinity therein con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tained,<note place="margin">
                  <hi>Sold by</hi> Giles Calvert.</note> I thought fit to commend unto thee this ensuing Book, called <hi>The late Assembly of Divines Confession of Faith examined:</hi> wherein many of their Excesses and Defects, of their Confusions and Dis<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>orders, of their Errors and Contradictions, are pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>sented, &amp;c. <hi>by a modest, but admirable sound Pen-man.</hi> It's apparent by this Treatise, there were many good Divines in <hi>England,</hi> besides those present in the As<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>sembly.</p>
            <p>There is also now published, <hi>Theatrum Chemicum
<pb facs="tcp:115088:41"/> Britannicum,</hi> containing severall Poeticall pieces of our famous English Philosophers, who have written the Hermetique Mysteries, or of the Philosophers Stone, in the English Tongue; published in honour of the English Nation, by <hi>Elias Ashmole,</hi> Esq; a Gen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tleman very learned, and a great lover of Antiqui<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ties. The Collection it self is of excellent Learning, and the Publishers Annotations on some hard places most ingeniously and profoundly performed.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>Rothmans Chiromancy,</hi> or, <hi>the Harmony of Chir<gap reason="illegible" resp="#keyers" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>man<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cy with Astrology;</hi> Englished by Capt. <hi>George Whar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ton:</hi> sold by <hi>Nathaniel Brooks.</hi> A piece of acurate Learning.</p>
            <p>There will be publique in Easter Term next, an excellent piece of <hi>Chiromancy</hi> and <hi>Metaposcopy,</hi> viz. <hi>rationall Judgement from the lines of the Forehad,</hi> by <hi>Richard Sanders,</hi> Student in <hi>Astrology.</hi> The like Work never extant in English. All sold by <hi>Natha<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>niel Brooks</hi> at the Angel in <hi>Cornhill.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>
               <hi>The Darknesse of Atheism dispelled by the Light of Nature:</hi> A learned and elaborate Treatise; is new<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly published, written by Doctor <hi>Charleton,</hi> Physitian to the late King. <hi>London,</hi> Printed for <hi>W. Lee</hi> at the Turks head in <hi>Fleet-street,</hi> 1652.</p>
         </div>
      </back>
   </text>
</TEI>